[ORGANISER] We will kick off [the event]
with a keynote on the future of money.
[Here] it really is about looking forward;
we had a stargazing session this morning.
[This speaker] is someone who doesn't need
a lot of introduction, other than to say...
that he is a world-class expert in his field, and has
come all the way to South Africa to talk to us.
Andreas Antonopoulos, welcome to South Africa
and welcome to the conference! [Applause]
[ANDREAS] Hi! Good morning, everyone.
I am so excited to be here.
This conference was called the
'Bitcoin Conference' a couple years ago;
now it is the 'Blockchain Conference.'
Next year, it will be "DLT Technology,"
and then the "Database Inspired By, But No Longer In
Any Way Related To, Blockchain" conference. [Laughter]
It is an interesting progression.
Let me do a quick poll of the audience.
I want [to see] your level of experience and familiarity
with this space, back to the yesteryears of Bitcoin.
How many of you currently own bitcoin? Fantastic.
For those who don't own bitcoin, how many of you have
ever conducted or seen a transaction happen in bitcoin?
Great. How many of you do not own any
cryptocurrency, of any type? Okay, great.
How many people are involved with Ethereum
and / or own ether? Great. Dash? Monero? Zcash?
Some interesting [answers].
How many of you own "blockchain"? [Laughter]
How many of you have used "blockchain"?
Other than in the five [coins] I mentioned previously.
All right, okay. A breakdown [of the answers] for those
of you who can't see what the audience is doing:
About 60 - 70% have bitcoin at the moment,
or have conducted a transaction.
About 30 - 40% [have ether], [with] smaller
minorities in Dash, Monero, and Zcash.
Nobody owns "blockchain."
This is interesting, this is exciting.
So, let's get started. What exactly is going on here?
Is this the greatest explosion of innovation since
the mobile internet, maybe even the internet itself,
or is this the greatest load of hype ever
arranged in the history of technology?
Both. [Hype] is a characteristic of
[emerging] advanced technologies.
I often say that where Bitcoin and other open
blockchains are today, is approximately where...
the internet was in 1992 --
in terms of [development stages], infrastructure
deployment, and adoption patterns.
This technology is approximately
where the internet was in 1992.
The hype around "blockchain" is where
the hype around the internet was in 1998.
You know what comes next.
There will be a shake-out.
When the waters recede, you can tell who on
the beach wasn't wearing a swimsuit. [Laughter]
They [will] stand there, naked as an empty promise.
This will happen in the blockchain space.
There is a lot of bullshit being peddled to venture
capitalists, to [educated and] uneducated investors.
There are a lot of Ponzi schemes,
pyramid schemes, empty promises,
and business-as-usual disguised as
innovation, as disruptive technology.
We are at this strange moment.
The underlying technology truly is
massively disruptive and innovative.
The amount of research happening today
in applied cryptography is unprecedented.
We are looking at [one of] the largest civilian
deployments of public key cryptography [besides SSL].
It turns out that people only protect keys
when those keys are attached to value.
Nothing teaches someone about security faster
than having their bitcoin on a Windows machine.
[Laughter] Holding your own bitcoin quickly
changes your attitude towards information security.
You didn't care about your photos; some of
you didn't even care about your sexy photos!
You didn't care about your location,
the fact that everything you do was tracked.
You didn't care about posting
your entire life on Facebook.
You use the same password ('password1234')
on seventeen different sites.
You didn't know what two-factor authentication was.
Then, Bitcoin happened.
Suddenly you're on a steep learning curve
and [becoming] better every day.
Now you tell your friends about
two-factor authentication.
You are horrified to remember
how you used to practice security.
Storing value has this unique ability to focus
your mind on the aspects of security that matter.
This technology is driving a
groundswell of security awareness.
It is driving the most incredible research
in applied cryptography we've ever seen.
Some of you are probably quite technical, involved
in computer science; you see what is happening here.
Nobody thought that we would be applying
Schnorr signatures or elliptic curve [in this way].
Nobody thought we would be applying ring signatures
and range proofs for confidential transactions.
The state of anonymity and
privacy is advancing rapidly.
We are building a whole new world
in terms of applied cryptography,
on [one of] the largest cryptographically-
secured networks the world has ever seen.
That is not business-as-usual. It is highly disruptive.
Out of [these developments] came this fantastic saying,
"Blockchain is the technology behind Bitcoin,"
which is incorrect.
The blockchain is one of the foundational technologies
behind Bitcoin, and it can't stand alone.
But that hasn't stopped people from
trying to sell "blockchain" [on its own].
"Blockchain" is Bitcoin with a haircut and
suit that you parade in front of your board.
It is the delivery of a sanitized, clean, comfortable
version of Bitcoin, to people who are too terrified...
[to] actually [build] disruptive technology.
This is a very strange world, where
the words no longer mean anything.
Can you define "blockchain" for me? I think a few people
in this room could probably define "blockchain."
The real challenge would be defining "blockchain"
in such a way that I can't do search-and-replace...
with the word "database," and
[those sentences still make sense].
If what you are [building] is a database with
signatures, it is not interesting. It is boring.
What is the essence of Bitcoin? It is not the blockchain.
The essence of Bitcoin is the ability to operate in a
decentralized way, without [needing] to trust anyone.
The essence of Bitcoin is independently verifying
everything yourself, without appeal to authority.
You don't trust the other nodes and miners you are
[connected] to. You assume [they may be] lying.
You don't trust people creating transactions.
You don't trust anything other than the outcome
of your own verification and validation.
You end up trusting something
more important: the network effect.
Bitcoin introduced decentralized security through
computation, and this has not yet sunk in.
Bitcoin allows you to replace a security model based
around concentric circles of access and control...
a [centralized] institution, with a security model
that is inside-out, open, and accessible to everyone.
The first security model based on market
forces and game theory, where [financial]...
incentives and punishments ensure that
you can trust the platform as a neutral arbiter,
which is not controlled by any one [entity].
[The Bitcoin network is] without third parties,
without intermediaries. Bitcoin revolutionizes trust.
It is difficult to have that conversation if you
only focus on Bitcoin. [Many] people have said,
"It is not just about currency.
What about the other applications?"
"It is not just about Bitcoin.
What about the other blockchains?"
In that sense, the term "blockchain" means
something, but only if you define it narrowly.
I use the qualifier "open" to talk
about blockchains [that matter].
I'm interested in the applications that
enable a decentralized, trustless system...
which does not rely on anyone as a
[trusted] intermediary. That is disruption.
That is the essence of this technology.
That essence is seen in other systems.
Ethereum exhibits it for smart contract applications.
Those smart contracts only work if you don't
[need] to trust anyone to execute it correctly.
You can only trust that will happen if everyone can
participate and verify each other in an open manner,
if access to the underlying consensus
algorithm and mining is open to everyone.
These characteristics [utilize] the [real]
power of these blockchain [systems].
Open. That is the key word.
Borderless. There are no borders.
Transnational. This is no longer about nation-states,
this is about network-centric trust without third parties.
The network is the trusted party,
but only if you verify everything.
Neutral. It isn't serving the goals of any one organization
or institution. Everyone follows the consensus rules.
There is no such thing as a 'good,'
'bad,' 'valuable,' or 'spam' transaction.
[There is no such thing as a 'legal' or 'illegal' transaction.
In these systems, there is only a 'valid' or 'invalid'
transaction, based on the consensus rules.
It doesn't matter who the sender is, who the recipient is,
what [scripts] or smart contracts are being executed.
Neutrality, radical neutrality.
Censorship resistance. To ensure that the system
is open, borderless, transnational, and neutral,
it must defend these properties by making it impossible
for any actor, or even several colluding actors,
to censor or blacklist users, restrict countries,
seize [bitcoin], or freeze transactions.
[All should be able to] participate in this network.
Those are important characteristics of
these open, decentralized systems of trust...
that do not depend on institutions.
I would like to equip you with a set of criteria
to understand when you are being presented...
with something -- perhaps to invest, [as part of your
employment], or to engage with in some other way --
[being called] a "blockchain" or "distributed ledger."
How can you tell? Blockchain or bullshit?
They both start with a 'b-,' but what's the difference?
If you can replace the word "blockchain" with
"database," and the brochure reads the same,
it's business-as-usual.
It [is probably] not decentralized, borderless,
neutral, censorship resistant, or open.
It [probably] re-establishes trust and intermediaries.
It is just a database. That is not disruptive.
The idea that we would use this technology to improve
operating margins of centralized institutions of trust,
so that they can continue business-as-usual...
I would say it is abhorrent, but that is a strong word.
It is just boring -- really, really boring.
No one [is interested in this technology
because they want] to make billions...
for a financial services clearinghouse;
if you did, I'm sorry, but that's boring. [Laughter]
What is exciting, is the possibility of fundamentally
changing the way we allocate trust on this planet,
opening up the ability to collaborate, transact,
and engage on a global level with everyone.
Simply by downloading an application,
you can become part of a giant platform...
that doesn't care who you are or where you came from.
It doesn't require permission to participate or innovate.
A twelve-year-old JavaScript programmer [could have]
the same influence and power as JPMorgan Chase.
[They will have] more [influence], in fact, because
they [are working on] open source [projects]...
feeding a community of collaboration that
is [generating] a tsunami of innovation.
[If you try to] take this technology and use it to
strengthen the same centralized institutions,
to improve their bottom line, [that] is boring.
That is not what a blockchain [is designed for],
that is just a database. It doesn't change anything.
There are some rather disturbing possibilities
in this model. Let's think about it for a second.
The application most commonly expressed
for these "distributed ledger technologies"...
is to replace the function of a centralized clearing
house with a consortium of 'n' participants,
where 'n' is two, three, four, ten etc.
known, permissioned participants.
They will [be allowed to] assemble transactions and
sign them, rather than compete [within the market]...
of a security model like Bitcoin.
[They will] discard currency as the underlying
mechanism for building market-based security.
[They will] discard proof-of-work as "wasteful,"
[even though that enables] a decentralized,
secure, neutral, and censorship-resistant blockchain.
We [will need to] trust five named
parties [to authorize] transactions.
[But if] they don't need to assemble these transactions
in blocks, because they sign individual transactions,
they don't need to chain them together.
Absent proof-of-work and a [reward] incentive,
rewriting [the chain] is easy. There is no immutability.
It is not a blockchain anymore.
There are no blocks and no chain.
[That was a] technical level [critique],
but let's look at the [political] level:
what do you achieve by replacing
a clearing house with a consortium?
[Supposedly], there is something
unique that a clearing house does.
If you understand the role of a clearing
house, one of its important functions...
is that it does not participate in the market;
it has no skin in the game.
The New York Stock Exchange is not an active trader.
That is not an accident, it is separation of concerns.
The clearing house is an independent party
with oversight that is not a market participant.
If you take that party out and replace it
with five banks that have skin in the game...
How do you run a consensus algorithm when there are
incentives to cheat, front-run, manipulate the market,
and break the consensus rules adversarially
against the other four parties?
There's no incentive to keep the consensus rules.
All you [can do] is say: "Trust us, we are in a
consortium." Trust you? Trust these five banks?
Where were you in 2008? Where were you when
Lieber was fixed, when gold markets were fixed?
Where were you when front-running and high-frequency
trading was creating monsters of crony capitalism?
"Trust us"? Hell no!
Replacing the clearing house with-
What is the word? It is not "consortium."
"Cartel,"" that's the word! [Laughter]
Replacing it with a cartel of the same market makers
who manipulated and compromised every market...
in history, in a way that [prevents] transparency...
That is not a recipe for efficiency, immutability, security,
or transparency. That is not a blockchain. It is bullshit!
It [may be] a very profitable bullshit, [but] it
requires you to have confidence in a con game.
Be careful [how] you evaluate these
technologies [when you see people]...
taking something with the fundamental
purpose of removing trusted intermediaries,
of creating an open, borderless, neutral system,
[while] turning it into a tool for untrustworthy
trusted parties, to manipulate markets.
It will be a disaster, but they will do it.
I [take] some consolation in
[knowing] that their keys will leak.
[In that] centralized system, [they must] secure the five
keys; none of them ever managed to do that [for long].
All the companies involved in this brave new
business-as-usual space have been hacked,
breached, leaked, and whistle-blown a dozen times.
They cannot keep [all of that]
information secure, no one can!
The whole point of a decentralized [system] isn't
keeping information secure [in one or a few places];
instead, you spread control out so thin
there is no place to attack it [all] directly.
That is what makes it secure. What happens when
you concentrate [control] among five participants?
I can't wait until Anonymous and WikiLeaks
collaboratively dump [the keys to the ledger]...
from the titans of Wall Street.
I can't wait, it [will be] so much fun. And it will happen,
because you cannot secure things [for long like that].
Does that mean there's nothing there [in blockchains]?
No. Again, we go back to the other side [of use cases].
This is an incredibly promising technology
based on an architecture of openness.
People are examining this market,
grasping and reaching out in darkness.
When you have a new disruptive technology, you can't
see the margins. It is like stumbling around a dark room.
Somewhere in there is a billion-dollar company,
an opportunity that will change the world,
that will have an impact on humanity.
Entrepreneurs look at people's problems
and see them as opportunities.
In 1997, when journalists were writing about
'the imminent failure of the internet'
and 'the impossibility of finding anything,'
Larry Page and Sergey Brin were finding stuff.
They built a multi-billion dollar empire on
solving the unsolvable problem of search.
There are seemingly unsolvable problems in
the open, decentralized, public, transparent,
neutral, censorship-resistant, global, trustless
network platform that is the blockchain.
Other blockchains, like Ethereum, are trying
to find their niche. Where are those markets?
There are three elements to success in this industry.
The first [factor] is identifying a viable market.
You [must] stumble in the dark and
find something useful [to do or build].
Very often, people stumbling in the dark
don't find anything useful [to do or build].
In 1998, Petco was building a online
commerce empire for pet supplies.
It was too early. The market didn't exist.
The web grocer, Webvan, was delivering groceries
to homes in San Francisco and failed miserably.
Was that the right market?
Maybe, but it was the wrong time.
That is the second important [factor]: timing.
You can identify [a niche] that, at some point, will
be enormous, but your [timing is] off by a decade.
Then the most important factor: sequencing.
[Establishing] the prerequisites.
Why wasn't Facebook [popular] in 1992?
[There wasn't] enough density of adoption.
[There weren't] mobile devices
that [could regularly] connect.
[There wasn't] even have home internet
that was permanently on, [like today].
[There weren't] dense online social networks so
you could engage with people you knew,
because [most of] the people you knew
barely [used] email or didn't even have email.
You can't build a complex system that depends on
[the interaction of many parts in] high density...
when you [only have] applications
that are one-to-one with low density.
To use an example from science: it [would be like]
trying to fuse hydrogen directly into carbon.
You can't do that. Helium, lithium, beryllium
[are in the way]. You have a long way to go.
[You must] keep smashing things together...
before you get enough density and can start
doing interesting things in organic chemistry.
You can't do advanced applications like retail
markets, real-estate and title, or voting [yet].
You can't do dense consumer-to-consumer markets or
[mass] point-of-sale retail with these systems yet.
You can't do most of the [applications] that
might [have] very interesting markets yet.
You can't do them yet because there are not enough
users or liquidity. There is not enough adoption.
The user interfaces are terrible;
applications are still at their infant stage.
That doesn't mean these things can't happen,
it just means they [will] not happen this year.
We [will] see [how] this plays out.
In order for people to put the title of their home on this
blockchain, it [must] be able to secure not billions,
but trillions of dollars in assets.
In order to secure trillions of dollars in assets,
it [must] have liquidity and infrastructure.
It [needs] broad adoption.
You [will not] get adoption [of an application] that most
people [may only] do twice in their lifetime, [if at all],
when you can't even [convince] them
to use it for day-to-day transactions.
We [will not build] digital identities so
that everyone can have a bank account.
It takes a long time until you have adequate adoption.
For the first fifteen years of the internet,
the [killer] application was email;
not until everyone had it, [needed to] have it
for work, did we see the second layer emerge.
That created the [necessary] density of adoption.
Currency is the email of blockchains.
Payments are the [killer application]
that will enable density of adoption.
It is very enticing to say,
"This is about more than money!"
Absolutely, in the long term, the vision
of this technology is far beyond money.
But you can't build [those future blockchain
applications] unless you first build the money part.
That is what creates the security, velocity, liquidity,
and the infrastructure. It funds the entire ecosystem.
In the end, when we deliver [these applications] to
people, [the purpose] won't be opening a bank account.
This isn't about banking the unbanked,
it is about de-banking all of us. Thank you. [Applause]