[IRVING GERSTEIN] Last week, the committee returned
to hearing [from] witnesses directly involved with...
one of the digital currencies: bitcoin.
The Bitcoin Embassy, the Bitcoin Alliance
of Canada, and the Bitcoin Foundation.
Today we are pleased to welcome
Mr. Andreas Antonopoulos.
[He is] considered to be the Bitcoin guru, and was
suggested to us by several previous witnesses.
Mr. Antonopoulos is both an entrepreneur
and an author in the field of Bitcoin.
He is a computer science graduate
from the University College London.
His expertise includes Bitcoin, cryptocurrencies,
information security, cryptography, cloud computing,
data centers, Linux, open source,
and robotics software development.
He has over two hundred articles
published and is syndicated worldwide.
In addition, he is a Certified Information Systems
Security Professional (CISSP) for over 12 years,
and a permanent host on the "Let's Talk Bitcoin" (LTB)
podcast, which is devoted to [discussing] Bitcoin.
Mr. Antonopoulos is also a prolific public speaker.
He recently appeared at the Toronto
Bitcoin Expo held earlier this year,
which I must tell our committee, our analysts attended.
Members of the committee, he has
literally written the book on Bitcoin, entitled:
"Mastering Bitcoin: Unlocking Digital Currencies."
It is with great pleasure that I turn the floor over
to Mr. Antonopoulos for his opening remarks,
to be followed by your astute questions.
Mr. Antonopoulos, welcome! The floor is yours, sir.
[ANDREAS] Thank you, Chair and committee members.
I appreciate the opportunity to contribute
to these proceedings about digital currency.
My [professional] experience is primarily in
information security and network architecture.
I have a master's degree in networks and distributed
systems, and have worked in the field since 1992.
I spent twenty years working on networks and
data centers for financial services companies...
before I found Bitcoin in late 2011.
I have been working full-time in the
Bitcoin space for the past two years,
and written a book on Bitcoin for software developers.
Today, I welcome the opportunity to talk to you about
Bitcoin's security, the decentralized architecture...
that underpins Bitcoin's security,
and the implications that architecture has for...
privacy, individual empowerment,
innovation, and regulation.
Until the invention of Bitcoin in 2008, security and
decentralization seemed like [opposing] concepts.
Traditional models for financial payment networks and
banking rely on centralized control to provide security.
The architecture is built around central
authorities such as a clearinghouse.
Authority must be vested in that central actor.
The resulting security model looks
like a series of concentric circles,
with very limited access to the center, [decreasing
power] as we move further away from the center.
Even the most outermost circle cannot
afford open access in such a security model.
The system is carefully protected by controlling access,
ensuring only vetted individuals and organizations...
can connect to it.
The entities near the center of the network are vested
with enormous power, act with full authority;
therefore, they must be very carefully
vetted, regulated, and subject to oversight.
Centralized financial networks can never be fully open
to innovation. Their security depends on access control.
Incumbents in such networks effectively utilize access
control to stifle outside innovation and competition,
presenting their actions as consumer protection.
Centralized financial networks are fragile and
require multiple layers of oversight to ensure that...
the central actors do not abuse their
authority and power for their own profit.
Unfortunately, the centralized architecture of
traditional financial systems concentrates power,
creating cozy relationships between industry insiders
and regulators, often leading to regulatory capture.
[The lack of] oversight leads to corruption,
and in the end, financial crises.
Bitcoin, and other digital currencies based on the
blockchain architecture, are fundamentally different.
The security model of blockchain currencies is
decentralized. There is no center to the network.
No central authority, no concentration of power,
no actor in whom complete trust must be vested.
Instead, the core security functions are put
in the hands of the end users of the system.
In this architecture, security is an emergent property of
the collaboration of thousands of network participants,
and not the function of a single authority.
In addition to the differences in architecture,
there are also fundamental differences...
in the nature of the payments themselves.
Digital currencies like bitcoin are much more
like cash than bank accounts or credit cards.
The transfer of value in Bitcoin is a
push mechanism, not a pull mechanism...
as is the case with credit cards, debit cards,
and most other digital payments.
A bitcoin payment is not an authorization
to pull [funds] from your account;
instead, it pushes the precise payment amount
as a value token directly to the [selected] recipient.
A single transaction does not authorize any
future transaction, or expose the user's identity.
The transaction itself is
unforgeable and unchangeable.
As a result, bitcoin payments can be transmitted
in the clear, without encryption, over any network.
[Transactions, though not keys], can be stored in
unsecured systems without fear of compromise.
Bitcoin's unique architecture and payment mechanism
has important implications for network access,
innovation, privacy, individual empowerment,
consumer protection, and regulation.
If a bad actor has access to the Bitcoin network,
they have no power over the network itself,
and can not compromise trust in the network.
This means the Bitcoin network can be open to
any participant without vetting, authentication,
identification, or prior authorization.
Not only can the network be open to anyone,
but it can also be open to any software application,
without prior vetting or authorization.
The ability to innovate without permission
at the edge is the same fundamental force...
that has driven internet innovation for twenty years at
a frenetic pace creating enormous value for consumers,
economic growth, opportunities, and jobs.
Bitcoin's decentralized nature affords
consumer protection in the most powerful way,
by allowing bitcoin users direct control over
the privacy of their financial transactions.
Bitcoin does not force users to surrender identity
with every transaction or put their trust in a [series]..
of supposedly vetted intermediaries...
who must be trusted to securely store and protect
transaction data and vulnerable account identifiers.
Bitcoin transactions never expose
vulnerable account identifiers.
Bitcoin users can protect the privacy of their
transactions without relying on any intermediaries.
In Bitcoin, trust is not vested in central actors, so there
is no need for centralized regulation and oversight.
When properly architected, Bitcoin financial services
are not vulnerable to central points of failure,
which would necessitate
heavy-handed oversight and regulation.
Instead, power lies with the end user, whose interests
are most aligned with the protection of their own funds.
While individual bitcoin wallets can be targeted
and compromised if not properly secured,
the network does not suffer
from centralized systemic risks.
Contrary to popular misconception,
Bitcoin is not unregulated.
Rather, several aspects of the
Bitcoin network and financial system...
are regulated by mathematical algorithms.
The algorithmic regulation in Bitcoin offers
predictable, objective, measurable outcomes,
such as a predictable rate of currency issuance.
These outcomes are not subject to the whims
of centralized institutions or committees,
which are both corruptible and often
placed outside of democratic oversight.
A bitcoin user can predict the monetary
supply thirty years from now, instead of...
hanging on the nuanced intonation of a single
adjective by some high official of central banking...
who can dramatically change an entire
country's monetary velocity a week hence.
Bitcoin's decentralized architecture does
not easily conform to the expectations...
or experiences of consumers and regulators.
Because there has never been a large-scale,
secure, decentralized network before.
The combination of decentralization and
security is the novelty at the heart of Bitcoin.
In trying to understand [how] consumer protection,
oversight, audits, and regulation [apply to] Bitcoin,
there is a risk that many will try to apply familiar models
of the past to this new digital currency system.
These models, designed to provide regulation
and oversight of centralized financial networks,
will seem familiar and be easier to understand.
However, they are inefficient and unsuitable for
this new form of decentralized financial network.
I urge you to resist the temptation to apply
centralized solutions to this decentralized network.
Centralizing Bitcoin [would] weaken its security, dull
innovative potential, and remove its most disruptive...
yet also most promising features.
Centralization will disempower users
while empowering incumbents.
Consumer protection will not be achieved by
removing Bitcoin's built-in privacy characteristics.
Demanding user identifiers, adding access control
mechanisms, and then trusting those identifiers...
to a chain of intermediaries, will only
replicate the failures of the past.
[This would] introduce single points of
failure into a network that has none.
We cannot protect consumers by removing
their ability to control their own privacy,
then asking them to entrust it in the same intermediaries
who have failed them so many times before.
Most failures in Bitcoin's security are the result
of misguided attempts at centralization,
such as removing control from the users.
In this new decentralized financial network, we have
the opportunity to invent new security mechanisms...
based upon innovations such as multi-signature
escrow, smart contracts, hardware wallets,
decentralized audits, and algorithmic proof of reserves.
These are the new decentralized regulatory
and security tools that are most appropriate...
for a decentralized digital currency.
Thank you for the opportunity
to address this committee.
[IRVING GERSTEIN] Thank you, Mr. Antonopoulos for
your opening remarks. They have clearly resonated...
and stimulated a number of questions.
But before I turn it over to senators for questions,
[first] I just might make an observation.
In your remarks, you have told the committee that the
decentralized security model of blockchain currencies...
is indeed secure, and that Bitcoin financial services
are not vulnerable to central points of failure which...
would necessitate oversight and regulation.
As a result, as I hear you, you have come to the
conclusion that this currency should be left...
hands-off by the government
and other regulatory bodies.
I quote, "Centralizing Bitcoin will weaken its security."
While listening very closely to your comments,
I couldn't help but observe that you made...
absolutely no mention of illegal activity
supporting a cryptocurrency like bitcoin.
I was surprised that you make no mention
of money laundering, terrorist financing,
or other possible misuses because of
the anonymous and open nature of Bitcoin.
I think you stated in your presentation that the Bitcoin
network can be open to any participant without vetting,
authentication, identification, or prior authorization.
I suspect that the misuse or potential misuse of bitcoin
for nefarious purposes is very much a concern...
to Canadians, as well as to this committee.
Would you have any comments on that?
Perhaps it may be picked up by some
of the senators in their questions as well.
[ANDREAS] Absolutely.
I believe there is a great misconception
in the idea that bitcoin use is anonymous,
or that the network itself is anonymous.
On the contrary, the public ledger allows any participants
to observe all transactions that occur on the network.
Those transactions are not tied to a specific identity,
but with the use of traditional law enforcement
mechanisms, when an identity is attached to...
a specific transaction, [those funds]
can be followed throughout the network.
Therefore, the network does not afford more anonymity.
In fact, it is easier to implement strong
transparency and accountability features...
than it is to achieve anonymity on the network.
Furthermore, I think bitcoin is not a
very convenient network for such uses.
The vast majority of such activities
really occur with cash, with the U.S. dollar.
I don't see bitcoin as the primary vehicle
for illicit activities of that type.
I see tremendous potential for the use of bitcoin
among the more than six billion people in the world...
who have very limited [or no] access to
international currencies, credit markets, and trade.
I think that use far outweighs the tiny minority
who might put such currencies to illicit use.
[IRVING GERSTEIN] Well, thank you for those
comments. With that, I will start with my list.
[Mixed discussion] [Laughter]
[IRVING GERSTEIN] When it is his turn,
we will turn it over to him for that.
Senator Black, to be followed by Senator Campbell.
[DOUGLAS BLACK] Thank you very much, Mr. Chairman.
Thank you very much, Mr. Antonopoulos...
[Interruption]
[IRVING GERSTEIN] Senator, please. Order.
[DOUGLAS BLACK] Thank you very much,
Mr. Antonopoulos, for being here.
I'm finding very real interest in what you have to say.
First of all, let me outline what I am
hoping to come to understand from you.
I'm interested in learning what is needed to
ensure that this innovation can continue to develop.
So that is my premise, right or wrong.
Building on the Chairman's initial comments,
I do have a question or two for you.
When CA Vertex testified before this committee,
they stated that they would like to see Bitcoin
regulations put in place as soon as possible,
to give clarity on how Bitcoin is classified.
They believe, and told this committee, that
this would allow Bitcoin to thrive in Canada.
In your remarks, you stated that Bitcoin should not
be regulated centrally because it will stifle innovation.
Considering that other groups have
echoed the statements of CA Vertex,
help me with a disconnect I'm hearing between the
evidence of CA Vertex and what you have said today.
[ANDREAS] Absolutely. I believe that the
best way to help Bitcoin is to ensure that...
there is clarity in the treatment of Bitcoin,
so that Bitcoin is not forced to contorting itself
into regulator structures that are designed...
by banks, for banks, [in the mind of] traditional
models of finance which are primarily centralized.
[It must be recognized] that bitcoin, as
programmable money, with capabilities...
such as digital multi-signature escrow,
has many more flexible ways of responding
to the need for consumer protection.
For example, in the traditional banking environment,
unless you hold cash, every account you have
as a consumer is a custodial account.
That means the funds are held in trust by a bank.
What you have in return is essentially a promise note
that the money will still be there tomorrow morning.
The bank controls the funds entirely.
Bitcoin allows for a more varied range of control
between consumers and financial services institutions,
from decentralized control, where the consumer or
end-user is the only one with full control over the money,
to complete custodial accounts, where a financial
services institution has full access to the keys,
while the consumer has none.
In between, there are also hybrid models.
The bank may have a signatory role, but would
not be able to change the direction of the funds.
They simply [sign] to approve transactions.
Within this very broad range of possibilities,
obviously some aspects of that do need regulation.
If you simulate a traditional financial environment with
custodial accounts and take full control of user funds,
then those funds are now outside
of the Bitcoin security model.
They are no longer protected by [decentralized]
control of keys in blockchain [security model].
Those [funds] are now in a gray area, not covered
by regulatory requirements for capital adequacy,
audits, and security controls, etc.
They are also not covered by the Bitcoin security model.
We have seen that whenever that
has happened, it results in disaster.
All of the exchanges that have been attacked
in Bitcoin had a full custodial model like that.
However, that is not the only model that exists.
There are digital bitcoin wallets
where the user has complete control.
There are wallets where the user has complete control,
but transactions cannot happen unless an additional
signature is placed by [another party or] institution...
that acts essentially as a risk manager, to ensure
that even if the user's system is compromised,
the money can't be stolen. A hybrid model.
If you lump all of those [models] together
under a single unifying [regulatory policy],
assuming that it is all just like a bank, then you will
miss out on opportunities to create better solutions...
with this new programmable money.
I do believe that certain models of bitcoin use must
be regulated, if control over user funds is centralized.
That institution puts consumers at risk.
But to lump in a decentralized model where
the user still has full control over their funds,
[maybe with] an institution which can't steal their money,
that same regulation is not only misguided, but it doesn't
leave any room for the technology to develop further.
[DOUGLAS BLACK] May I ask one further question?
Thank you very much for that.
What would you suggest to this committee
in terms of regulation [for Bitcoin], if any?
[ANDREAS] I believe, we are still at
the very early stages of this technology.
Not only is Bitcoin new, but Bitcoin is already evolving.
For example, the capability to do a multi-signature
transaction with up to twenty different signatories.
A transaction can be controlled
by a mixture of signatures.
That [scheme] was introduced in 2012,
four years after the introduction of Bitcoin.
[That became] available in 2013, so Bitcoin is already
developing new, exciting programmable capabilities...
for user security.
I think this technology needs time to breathe.
It needs time to show the full potential of what is =
possible with decentralized programmable money.
Until that time, I think [we can] open up those
possibilities by making clear distinctions...
where the technology allows it, for example between
centralized and decentralized modes of operation,
and understanding those nuances, can create niches for
new players to come in to the financial services market.
[This will] introduce innovation, competition,
and disruption into the banking industry...
by trying out new models for consumer protection,
which in my opinion are superior
to the ones we have today.
[DOUGLAS BLACK] So your answer is what,
in terms of what this committee should do, if anything?
[ANDREAS] Wait until the technology
is better understood by all of us.
Understand that there are nuances
that require very careful treatment.
[Not] a blanket treatment that this is just a currency,
which it is not. It is a network for money.
[Not] a treatment as if there is only one
application, the bitcoin currency, which it is not.
There are many applications based on this model.
[A blanket treatment] would stifle
this technology in its early days.
[DOUGLAS BLACK] Thank you very much. Mr. Chairman.
[IRVING GERSTEIN] Thank you, Senator Black.
Senator Campbell, to be followed by Senator Greene.
[LARRY CAMPBELL] Thank you, Chair.
And thank you so much for coming today.
I remember when I got an IBM Selectric that
had a backspace so that I could correct letters.
And I thought, 'Nothing will ever be cooler
than this. It's impossible.' [Laughter]
I am 67 years old. That is my generation.
Would it be fair- You say it needs some breathing space.
Would it be fair to say that the younger generation
[understands Bitcoin] more so than my generation?
[ANDREAS] With any new technology,
I think that is the case.
[LARRY CAMPBELL] Do you think it is fair to say-
For instance, I would doubt very much that I will...
get into bitcoins, because I don't really understand it
even though we are on our 11th meeting. [Laughter]
[UNKNOWN] We are lucky that Paul does.
[LARRY CAMPBELL] Yes, Senator Massicotte does.
But when I talk to younger people about this committee,
they totally get it and don't have any questions at all.
They say, "This is where we are going and how we will
get there." I've been told to keep my old nose out of it.
[Laughter] I think you explained it.
How much time does it take for this to breathe?
How long do you think that would be?
I mean, how rapid will this come upon us?
[ANDREAS] I would estimate that Bitcoin today,
is approximately [where] the internet was in 1992.
In 1992, when I used email, that required
command line Unix skills, typed into a mainframe.
It was very difficult. Approximately ten years [later],
it had already reached mainstream adoption...
especially among younger people.
Almost exactly twenty years [later], my mother got
her first iPad and was able to send her first email.
It took some while until the technology
went from something extremely esoteric,
only the purview of someone working
in a computer science department,
until my mother could do it with a swipe of her finger,
and she is a self-acknowledged technophobe.
So [Bitcoin] may take some time [too].
What I can tell you, for sure, is that
it will [happen] about three times faster.
Because we are [mostly] not deploying physical
infrastructure and already have the internet...
as a medium on which we can spread this,
I believe we will see very mainstream
applications with eight years that will be...
much easier to use and secure.
[These applications] will allow consumers to
use bitcoin in a way that feels very comfortable.
At the moment, we are not there.
[LARRY CAMPBELL] Okay, just one more question.
The question I have is, if you don't need any
centralized oversight, who provides it [in Bitcoin]?
I mean, you say the end-user controls the whole thing.
If there is nobody finding out who the end-user is, how
can we be sure that ISIS or another whack-job crew...
[won't] use this as a method of
transferring money around the world?
[ANDREAS] I firmly believe that the possibility
for positive uses of this technology far outweighs...
the very small possibility for negative uses.
The truth is, ISIS is probably using pallets of money
that they stole from [the United States and its] allies...
during their reign of terror, and not bitcoin.
I think it is a matter of understanding that limiting
technology which has the [potential] to bring...
economic inclusion to billions
of people who do not have it today,
in the same way that cellphones allowed entire nations
to leapfrog the landlines and achieve communication...
that would be unthinkable
[in prior realms of technology],
Bitcoin can do the same for banking and finance.
It can empower billions of people around
the world in areas such as remittances,
accessing international finance, credit,
liquidity, loans, and things like that.
As with any technology, this technology will reflect
society, with a tiny minority who may use it for evil.
I have full faith that the law enforcement capabilities,
properly exercised, could follow funds on Bitcoin,
just as they can in the traditional
financial networks, and probably more so.
Furthermore, I think bitcoin is the most
open and transparent of cryptocurrencies.
There are already about five hundred others.
I believe that if Bitcoin is not given the opportunity
to work in a way that empowers people,
eventually [any] criminals will move to far more stealthy
and less open currencies, and use those instead.
[LARRY CAMPBELL] Thank you. Thank you very much
for coming today. I very much appreciate it.
[IRVING GERSTEIN] Thank you, Senator Campbell.
Senator Greene, to be followed by Senator Massicotte.
[STEPHEN GREENE] Thank you very much for coming.
Without question, this is the most
interesting topic we have looked at...
since I have been a member of the committee.
I am just amazed by-
One of the things I was thinking about
last night as I was reading your paper,
the idea that occurred to me,
and I want you to comment on it,
is that bitcoin and related currencies are not
hackable, because there is nothing to hack.
Is that a true statement? I wonder, if it is,
could explain that in very simple terms?
Because I imagine there are
a lot of people watching this.
[ANDREAS] Individual bitcoin wallets,
such as my wallet, can be hacked.
We see examples of that [happening].
But the system as a whole cannot be hacked.
I say that with confidence because, over the last five
years, especially recently in the last year and a half,
the value transferred over the Bitcoin network
[in that time] exceeded $5 billion U.S. dollars.
There has been no shortage
of people trying to hack Bitcoin.
If anything, Bitcoin has changed the
dynamics of cybercrime and hacking.
The attacks have escalated. Bitcoin created
a target for hackers that is extremely fluid,
residing on [many] people's computers.
They have tried to take advantage of that.
But I know that Bitcoin [as a system] can't be hacked,
simply because many people have been trying...
non-stop for the past five years and can't hack it.
There is a very big difference between the system
as a whole, which is dynamic and responds to attacks,
and individual wallets.
I think you will see a very similar
development timeline as with the internet.
I remember a time when groups of hackers could
take down Yahoo, Microsoft, and Google for a day.
They don't do that anymore,
but not because they stopped trying.
A dynamic system that is constantly exposed
to threatening stimuli will develop resistance...
to these types of attacks.
This is a concept often called "anti-fragility."
It becomes dynamically stable and resistant to attack.
Bitcoin is not static. It continuously evolves,
dealing with attacks better and better over time.
[STEPHEN GREENE] Thanks very much, very interesting.
You mentioned in the answer to the previous question...
that there are roughly five hundred other
cryptocurrencies. [ANDREAS] Mm-hmm.
[STEPHEN GREENE] What is the size of Bitcoin
in relation to those? Are they major competitors?
Or are they copy-cats?
[ANDREAS] I would say, for the most part,
that they are just copy-cats.
My personal opinion is that the
allocation of cryptocurrencies...
(in terms of market size, adoption by users, etc.)
follows a long-tail or power-law distribution curve,
where the vast majority is concentrated in
one or maybe a [small] handful of currencies,
and then you potentially have a tail that stretches out
to encompass thousands of smaller currencies.
Being able to [start] currencies at whim creates
an environment where there will be thousands...
possibly tens of thousands of currencies in the future,
but only a handful have economic viability, market value.
That doesn't change the [potential], in my opinion,
for people to create currencies
the way they create internet memes.
In many cases, they will be internet memes.
We have seen that happen in [crypto]currencies.
What is happening here is a laboratory of [technological]
evolution and innovation, where new ideas are tested.
Some of the best results are often catastrophic failure
on a small scale that informs future designs for Bitcoin.
[STEPHEN GREENE] It's amazing. Do you foresee a
time when, in the interests of economic development..
what-have-you, that a nation state [would] decide
to forgo its own currency and adopt bitcoin?
[ANDREAS] That is a difficult question.
I think the very nature of currency is changing.
The economy, or 'organization' if you like,
adopting the bitcoin currency is the internet.
That is a transnational entity.
I think that has even more important implications
for the future than national currencies.
Bitcoin is already bigger than some national currencies;
it may end up being more important for economic
activity than dozens of smaller national currencies.
I do foresee that national central banks
may utilize blockchain technology to...
underpin national digital currencies.
[STEPHEN GREENE] Great. Thank you.
[IRVING GERSTEIN] Thank you, Senator Greene.
Senator Massicotte, to be followed by Senator Wells.
[PAUL MASSICOTTE] Thank you, Chair. Thank you for
being with us. It is obviously very interesting and useful.
Let me follow up on the question from our Chair.
[In] your presentation, you discourage us from
even recommending some form of identification.
I think your argument is, [transactions] are always
be visible; you are right, the chain is very visible.
But what you don't see in a chain is, who is
behind the chain. And that is why I would presume...
people with illegal objectives
or means are prepared to use it.
They apparently are using this mechanism
to transfer and launder money.
I gather your argument is: 'I recognize that is a negative
[use case], but don't hesitate because of that issue.'
'Don't put measures in place to restrict that flow,
because the usefulness of those measures in...
identifying who is behind the transfers, will
be less than the usefulness to our society...
in letting this thing develop. Is that accurate?
The chain is visible, but not the identity of the persons,
which is what I think the Chairman was asking about.
[ANDREAS] I am recognizing two aspects:
[first], attempts at imposing identity on Bitcoin...
will be ineffective because there will always be
channels by which non-identifiable transactions...
can be introduced, either in Bitcoin or other
currencies, while simultaneously removing...
one of the greatest advantages.
Senator, today I have received three automated
phone calls from Visa fraud prevention just because...
I used my card in Canada.
They have been calling me all day. This is something
that happens to me every time I travel.
This is a symptom of releasing an identifier
that allows others to pull from my account...
and ties every transaction I [send] to every activity I do.
I am not only giving up my privacy, but endangering my
personal financial security every time I use a credit card.
This system is non-viable.
I watch every few weeks on the news that yet another
[company] has lost fifty million consumer credit cards,
or identity [documents] lost; for the average consumer,
that is months of identity protection and risk.
These are the intermediaries who handle our identities.
Over the last two decades, we have seen that protecting
[centralized] information systems in such a way...
that we can prevent these
types of thefts, is not possible.
The mistake is tying identity to every transaction,
and creating systems that can continuously
draw [money] from our accounts.
Bitcoin is fundamentally different. To break that in order
to tie identities, which anyone can easily bypass...
if they have [enough] ill intent, would not result
in protecting us more, but harming consumers.
[PAUL MASSICOTTE] The conclusion being, you
acknowledge that this system could encourage...
money-laundering, but you're arguing to not do anything
about it, because the benefits for society from this...
form of transfer is more important.
Is that your argument?
I gather that is what you're saying.
[ANDREAS] My argument is that, [regardless of]
the invention [and use] of blockchain technologies,
any of these systems to be used for
ill intent, with [or without] identity.
There is nothing that can be done to stop someone-
[PAUL MASSICOTTE] Nor should even try to stop.
[ANDREAS] I think that would harm the
vast majority of people who do good with it.
[PAUL MASSICOTTE] Let me talk to you about...
We are a little bit older than you are, but...
Every time we achieve certain points in life-
I guess we could look at central banks
because we are the banking committee.
They come across new theories every
twenty to thirty years about how to control...
money supply, growth, and inflation.
Then we always learn thirty or forty years later,
'Sorry, we got it wrong. Shit happens,' in other words.
Having said that, when I look at your algorithm-
You say we will predict the necessary growth...
of this currency as a form of transfer, and we got it right.
But I highly suspect that twenty to thirty,
I will say, "Well, you didn't get a right."
Clue me in: what would be the one or two things
that you got wrong when you project the future?
Where are the one or two
weaknesses where you can say,
"I could have been wrong;
here is where I may have gone wrong"?
[ANDREAS] What is useful to understand is, Bitcoin's
monetary policy is just one recipe that is possible.
Bitcoin and other currencies like that allow us
to implement monetary recipes at will,
and then fix [or replace] them.
If Bitcoin's monetary recipe is wrong,
people will move to another currency...
that has the same characteristics of decentralized
organization, but with a different monetary recipe.
It is simply one of the possible choices.
I don't know if it is the right or wrong monetary policy,
but I do know what Bitcoin's [issuance rate] will be in
thirty years years, down to the millionth decimal point.
Exactly how many currency units will exist in 140 years.
What it provides, whether you like that recipe or not,
whether you agree with it or not, is certainty.
It provides predictability. It allows
people to adjust their expectations.
Whether that is right or wrong monetary policy...
Well, with this new model, you can build your own
currency which has a different monetary policy.
And if it is better, it [will] win [in the market].
It is an open competition.
[PAUL MASSICOTTE] The supply is defined by
the algorithm. But people like our Chairman...
who [could have] bought this unit [of
currency], maybe the supply is limited,
But if [the price] will be equal to the demand
growth, who knows [where the price will go]?
[ANDREAS] Nobody knows. [PAUL MASSICOTTE]
The price of that currency may fluctuate immensely...
if you got [the monetary policy] wrong.
The purpose of the algorithm is to project,
as reasonable as it can, that future growth.
But it may not be.
Maybe the supply is defined, but not the price.
Therefore, if you get high fluctuation of value,
that will discourage its use [as a currency].
[ANDREAS] Absolutely, but at the moment volatility
is a reflection of very low liquidity in bitcoin.
Bitcoin has a very specific recipe that simulates
the supply curve of precious metals like gold.
That is a very specific monetary theory.
If there is a different monetary theory, you can build
a different currency using blockchain technology.
You could even build a blockchain technology
currency where the monetary supply is defined...
by a committee of twelve central bankers,
and then invite users / consumers to adopt it.
It would still be more transparent
than our current system of money.
[PAUL MASSICOTTE] Thank you, Chair.
[IRVING GERSTEIN] Thank you.
Senator Wells, to be followed by Senator Ringuette.
[DAVID WELLS] Thank you very much, Chair.
I am pleased to be here today, filling in for someone.
As we ran into each other earlier today, you said this
would be an exciting committee meeting, and it is.
Mr. Antonopoulos, thanks for coming
and thanks for your answers so far.
Who are Bitcoin's biggest detractors,
and why are they enemies of Bitcoin?
[ANDREAS] I am not sure who Bitcoin's
biggest detractors are, but I can tell you that...
I -- and every other passionate advocate
I know -- started off as a detractor.
It is important to note that my initial response to Bitcoin
was, "This is nerd money and it can't possibly work."
[Laughter] In fact, when Satoshi Nakamoto invented
Bitcoin and announced it on the cyherpunk mailing list,
everyone around him responded
in pretty much the same way.
The circle of advocates, which is now numbering in the
millions, consists of people who started as sceptics.
The first time I saw it, that was my reaction.
The second time, I read the whitepaper...
and understood that this was not [just] a currency.
It is a decentralized network model for financial
security and trust which [relies on] currency,
but also allows for many other things.
That literally blew my mind, and then
I understood this was much bigger.
We all started out as skeptics. I don't know
if all the skeptics become advocates over time,
but I do see that people who look at Bitcoin carefully
understand there is a lot more than meets the eye.
[DAVID WELLS] What would Bitcoin's
biggest threat to growth [and adoption] be?
[The need] for people to overcome fear
of the unknowns? The security aspect?
The level of technology available?
The individual nodes might not have
the security that the whole system has.
[ANDREAS] There are some very significant
security problems related to the ownership...
and control of bitcoin keys in wallets for end-users.
The simple truth is, we have been [studying] information
security as an industry for a handful of decades.
That industry is not very effective at doing it, whether
in trying to protect credit card [details] or bitcoin.
The nice thing about bitcoin is, the risk is
compartmentalized. There is no systemic risk.
Over time, we will see the development of more
secure mechanisms like hardware wallets,
such as the ones beginning
to appear in the market today.
For every problem I see in Bitcoin, as an entrepreneur
I simultaneously see a tremendous opportunity.
If you look back at the history of disruptive technologies,
in 1994 there were dozens and dozens of articles...
about how the internet would fail because no one
would ever be able to find anything on the internet.
Sergey Brin and Larry Page decided
that was an opportunity, not a problem.
With Bitcoin, in each one of these problems lies a new,
innovative financial industry that can offer solutions.
[DAVID WELLS] Thank you.
I have one more question, Chair, if I may.
Of the millions of users a bitcoin currently,
who would constitute the biggest user group?
International financial transactions?
What is the user group with the highest plurality?
[ANDREAS] I think there are a few statistical
surveys that provide some insight into that.
I'm not sure about the exact numbers.
I think the most common use for bitcoin is...
charitable giving, donations and [online] tipping.
The demographics, at the moment,
are very similar to the early internet:
a narrow [set] of technology professionals.
A lot of nerds in this space,
I can say that for sure.
But it just follows the same [adoption] path as
any other technology, becoming more appealing...
to a broader demographic over time.
For me, the most interesting thing is not what
Bitcoin can do for western developed countries.
We have fairly sophisticated banking systems.
I am fascinated by the idea of deploying Bitcoin on
a Nokia feature phone in Kenya or Lagos, Nigeria...
This would people who have never had access
to financial services online into a global economy...
with international credit, connected to
everyone else in the world on equal footing.
That is very exciting to me; that is where
the greatest need lies that Bitcoin can fulfill.
[DAVID WELLS] Okay. Thank you, Chair.
[IRVING GERSTEIN] Thank you, Senator Wells.
Senator Ringuette, to be followed by Senator Meredith.
[PIERRETTE RINGUETTE] Thank you, Chair.
Most impressive. When you started out
by saying that you have spent 20 years...
working on networks and data centers
for financial services companies, I say,
they must be in dire need to hire you back! [Laughter]
[UNKNOWN] He is not for sale.
[PIERRETTE RINGUETTE] No, but-
With all the knowledge you have
gathered about cryptocurrency...
What would be your guess for development
to create a similar cryptocurrency?
[ANDREAS] I'm not sure I understand the question.
[PIERRETTE RINGUETTE] Well, as you said,
there are over about hundred
different cryptocurrency networks.
What would be the cost to develop and
create a similar cryptocurrency to bitcoin?
[ANDREAS] Well, every day, somebody decides that
Bitcoin isn't the correct answer, they have a better one,
and choose to try and build a better cryptocurrency.
Blockchain technology has taken the very
natural inclination of people to create currency...
as a form of language and expression
of value, which exists in every society.
From pre-historic times with beads and feathers,
to modern times with all the forms of currency...
that existed before nationalized monopoly money.
That possibility, of not only creating a currency,
but that currency being global, secure, fast,
predictable, and transparent...
It means a ten-year-old can create
a currency that is as secure as...
the currency created by a monarch a few centuries ago.
Just like the internet brought desktop publishing
and communications into the hands of individuals,
enable a capability that was previously only the
purview of those who had [large] printing presses,
blockchain technology has democratized
access to [the tools of] currency creation.
As a result, anyone with the impulse to create currency,
for reasons completely serious or trivial, can now do so.
That currency [could become]
global, secure, and unforgeable.
[PIERRETTE RINGUETTE] Without cost?
[ANDREAS] Without cost.
In fact, you can go onto a website
and create RinguetteCoin today.
[PIERRETTE RINGUETTE] I would love that! [Laughter]
[ANDREAS] For a fifth of a tenth of a bitcoin.
For a very small amount, in any case.
Very soon, that will be free.
I do anticipate that you will see coins created by
children, performers, entertainers, football teams...
Most of them will only have entertainment value,
but some of them may surprise us and cross over...
into the realm of economic value.
[Bitcoin] changes the fundamental relationship between
individuals and currency as a form of expression.
[PIERRETTE RINGUETTE] The second question I have...
You said, individual bitcoin wallets can be targeted
and compromised if not properly secured.
How can one properly secure [their] bitcoin wallet?
[ANDREAS] With great difficulty right now.
It requires great technical skill,
which is one of the issues that needs
to be addressed over the next few years...
in order to make bitcoin more
accessible to mainstream users.
Right now, it is difficult to do so.
Our individual computer systems are not
designed to secure purely digital money...
that resides on your iPhone or desktop.
For experts and specialists, there are new devices which
have come out, with wallets embedded in hardware.
Small devices that you plug into your computer
and all the bitcoin keys are only held on that device.
I actually print out my bitcoin keys on paper,
and then put them in a fireproof safe.
I store a second copy in a bank safe deposit box...
which is ironic because I'm securing my bitcoin
by putting [the keys] in a bank vault. [Laughter]
Making the keys physical actually allows me to impart
the greatest form of security that I know how to use.
Physical security is something we're more familiar with.
Information security [research] is
accelerating because of bitcoin.
A lot of innovation is happening in
that space, which is very exciting.
[PIERRETTE RINGUETTE] Third question.
You indicated that a person could acquire
a loan in bitcoin. How would one go about that?
[ANDREAS] There are already organizations
implementing a concept called peer-to-peer lending,
which exists in the traditional currencies.
For example, there are companies like LendingClub.com
where I can make a loan to a fellow American.
They will end up paying a lower interest rate than
for credit cards, and I will actually get an interest rate...
that is higher than I would with a certificate of deposit.
If I diversify my loans enough,
only investing a small amount in each loan,
I will suffer a pretty low default rate.
[With Bitcoin], that [scheme] can become global.
I could lend money with bitcoin to someone...
anywhere in the world, and there
are companies already doing this.
In that case, I would invest perhaps in
two to three thousand different loans so...
default on one loan wouldn't affect
my entire my entire amount.
[I would] diversify my risk that way. This has
tremendous implications for world-wide credit.
It not only allows people in the developing world
to source credit, but people in the developed world...
can invest their money directly with the borrowers,
without intermediaries, at a much lower cost.
[PIERRETTE RINGUETTE] Well, yeah,
but you have an intermediary for this.
You have this organization that [facilitates] what you are
prepared to loan, and people wanting to acquire loans.
So you have this intermediary?
[ANDREAS] Today, we have. Yes, indeed.
But with bitcoin, this is one of the
tremendous things that is happening.
Many of the traditional financial services
can now be redesigned and re-envisioned...
in a completely decentralized
fashion, without intermediaries.
This concept of disintermediation, or removing
intermediaries, connecting buyers the sellers directly,
consumers to merchants, [borrowers] to
creditors, is the magical power of Bitcoin.
That is what this invention has allowed us to do,
without [needing] to first establish trust.
With Bitcoin, we can have a completely
decentralized market for credit and lending...
that is simultaneously global, near instantaneous,
and allows access to a vast pool of credit.
That is a very exciting prospect.
[PIERRETTE RINGUETTE] Okay. From your perspective..
and Chair, this is my last question.
If Canada would move forward with some regulation,
as some witnesses have asked of us,
and the [rest of] the world, the G7 countries,
did not follow us with similar regulation,
what would the pros and cons of such a move be?
[ANDREAS] Well, that is a very interesting [question].
We already see tremendous regulatory fragmentation.
A regulator in New York State has taken initiative to
regulate based on [existing] New York State laws,
regulation that looks very similar to traditional banking
regulations and is not very well suited for Bitcoin.
Simultaneously, there will be other forms of regulation.
In the United States, we will likely end up with
a patchwork of federal, state, and local regulations.
You will see similar attempts in many countries.
Bitcoin technology is such that it can
operate across borders very effectively.
Therefore, Bitcoin companies can migrate
to the areas of least friction, create new jobs,
[contribute] innovation and growth in the places
where regulation is best informed about the nuances..
and particular needs of Bitcoin companies.
Canada and other countries which are
looking at this regulation very carefully,
rather than rushing into it, have an opportunity to create
a very friendly environment to those companies.
They will attract one of the industries that,
quite frankly, is creating thousands of jobs today,
which cannot be said for too many other industries.
[PIERRETTE RINGUETTE] Thank you.
[ANDREAS] Thank you.
[IRVING GERSTEIN] Thank you very much.
Senator Meredith, to be followed by the
Deputy Chair, Senator Hervieux-Payette.
[DON MEREDITH] Thank you so much, Chair.
Thank you so much for your presentation.
As I was reading your notes last night-
This is a segue into what my colleague just raised...
with respect to regulations.
Our committees here in the Senate are looking to put
forward recommendations in a report to government...
that will hopefully become law to protect Canadians.
You talked to us about individuals being hacked.
Companies who you cited earlier have spent millions
and millions of dollars on their security architecture,
to protect the data provided by consumers.
We see how vulnerable they are,
how this data has been lost.
Major banks have come and indicated that
they have been hacked months [after the fact],
to the surprise of their customers whose credit cards,
[identity and financial] data is now out there.
Now you are advocating a decentralized system.
The traditional banking system is predicated on
all these security measures to protect consumers.
We are about protecting Canadians, so bring
[this discussion] back as to how we would do that...
going forward with Bitcoin and what you're proposing.
I understand the rationale of [open] access,
especially when it comes to Africa, for example.
and the other outlying areas.
We have seen how the revolution of cellphones
has changed the dynamics of communication,
as well as financial transactions.
Talk to us about the security aspect.
How would we go forth with respect to protecting
Canadians who are or become engaged in [Bitcoin]?
[ANDREAS] One of the big failures of regulation
in the traditional [financial] environment is,
with centralized identifiers and regulation
comes the centralization of risk.
When an organization such as Home Depot or Target
is hacked, losing sixty million consumer identities,
the reason that [hack] had such an enormous impact...
is because they were storing sixty million
consumer identities in the first place.
Instead, if each of those sixty million consumers
[needed] to be individually targeted and hacked,
the possibility of that happening is much lower.
The advantage of a decentralized environment is,
there is no central repository, motherload, or vault...
where everyone's identity is stored
and can be attacked at the same time.
Bitcoin proposes a different model where the risk and
control are pushed out into the hands of the users.
The result is a system that is much
more resilient against systemic risk.
That means users themselves have enormous power;
with that power, they also have responsibility.
That control exposes them to individualized risk.
[DON MEREDITH] How do we mitigate that risk, though?
[ANDREAS] That risk is already being mitigated...
by [various] innovations [and training].
On one hand, you have this increased
exposure of the individual one-by-one;
on the other hand, we have programmable money,
which allows us to invent new models for security.
Whether those are specialized devices that control keys and never expose them to the internet,
or multi-signature transactions where a number
of signatures are required to release funds.
Those signatures could belong to two
different devices that one user [owns].
For example, they need to authorize a transaction
from their laptop and their mobile phone,
which gives them a greater degree of security.
You could have secondary or tertiary controls
stored on paper, on a device that is kept offline,
in a vault at home, or a fireproof safe.
Those are the very basic [procedures]
that we are following right now.
But we are already seeing companies
providing services to consumers...
where they look at every [outgoing] transaction
and provide a third signature to authorize it,
based on a risk assessment.
In that case, the company has no
custodial control over the funds.
All they can do is sign or not sign the transaction.
They are providing a risk check, and just that.
These are very interesting models
we have never explored before,
because neither the user had enough control, nor was
the network open enough to allow experimentation.
The technology underlying it wasn't flexible enough.
I have great faith. Already, just in the last two years
as this technology has gone [more] mainstream,
the amount of innovation around that exact
problem has accelerated tremendously.
We are gradually beginning to win
in terms of protecting end-user wallets.
In this area specifically, requiring users to attach identity
to every transaction and put all of those [identities]...
in a central repository, just like the regulations
in New York have demanded, is folly to me.
It takes away the one opportunity we have
to think of a different way of doing this,
and expose us to the same systemic risk of centralized
points of failure that we have with credit cards.
I'm hoping that the market will be
allowed to develop these solutions.
[DON MEREDITH] Going forward with what one of
my colleagues, Senator Black, raised with respect to...
breathing time, and you indicated this as well...
What would be a suitable timeframe for us to look?
Obviously, this is evolving and in development.
However, we believe there needs to be
some sort of regulations put in place,
similar to what we have done with the internet in terms
of privacy, requests for information, and so forth.
With respect to the breathing time,
if we were to enact some sort of legislation,
give us your opinion as to what that would look like,
to govern Bitcoin and its transactions.
[ANDREAS] If we look at the
experience with the internet,
the opportunity for the internet to develop its own
models for self-regulation was extremely effective.
It delivered a lot of good to a lot of people.
Ironically, when the U.S. Senate finally came around
to regulating spam, that was the same year...
that technology solved the problem.
In some cases, waiting is the better option.
I don't think there is a major problem with
consumer access to bitcoin at the moment,
in terms of the risk it poses to consumers.
However, there are particular areas where
I believe your committee could offer clarity.
The first one is making a clear distinction
between centralized, custodial accounts,
and decentralized models of bitcoin operation.
Not lumping them together.
Centralized custodial accounts
are dangerous to consumers.
They expose consumers to the exact same risk
of [traditional] centralized financial institutions,
only in this particular case, there is still zero
oversight or control over these institutions.
They [often] operate outside
of the banking environment.
For example, when CA Vertex came here and asked for
regulation, in that environment, that is a sensible idea.
CA Vertex has complete control of user keys
and operates in a centralized, custodial manner.
However, I think we should leave opportunities
for the development of decentralized solutions,
and recognize that those are neither
subject to the same risks for consumers,
nor do they need the same types of regulation custodial accounts.
That would open up a lot of possibility
for innovation in that space.
I think it is also important to carve out exceptions.
There are exceptions already in existing law,
in terms of personal exchanges of small accounts.
For example, if I exchange a small amount of U.S.
dollars for Canadian dollars on the street corner,
I will not be arrested for operating
without the money transmitting license.
It is important to recognize that, on a small scale and
for personal use, there should be clarity in the law...
that you don't require licenses to operate...
and personal use as a consumer is not
subject to banking-level regulation.
That would be very useful in allowing
further development of this technology.
[DON MEREDITH] One final question, Chair.
He indicated that there is a small percentage of
bad actors. What systems do you currently have...
in place to deal with those individuals
who would abuse the system?
[ANDREAS] Traditional law enforcement has been
tremendously successful in tracking and stopping...
such activities on the network, again and again.
So far, I haven't heard of any particular need
for changing the way the network operates.
In fact, such a request would be met with no
[such] change, because this is a global network.
It isn't under the control of a single individual. I don't
control Bitcoin any more than anybody else controls it.
The network itself provides a level of transparency
that law enforcement can use [to track that activity].
[DON MEREDITH] Thank you. Thanks, Chair.
[IRVING GERSTEIN] Deputy Chair of the committee,
Senator Hervieux-Payette,
to be followed by Senator Tkachuk.
[HERVIEUX-PAYETTE] [Translated from French]
Thank you. In view of the fact that no one has...
spoken in French so far, I will be
putting my questions in French.
Can you tell me whether there are countries, at the
present time, that recognize and supervise Bitcoin?
[ANDREAS] I believe that there are several countries
in which Bitcoin use has been recognized,
in many different ways and at different
levels of the legislative or judicial process.
In terms of recognizing, in fact, that bitcoin is money,
that it is subject to the same rules and
regulations around taxation and operation,
and that it also carries certain liberties such
as freedom of association and expression.
Within many countries, bitcoin fits comfortably
within the existing system for currencies.
However, I don't know whether any country
required legislation specifically for bitcoin,
[HERVIEUX-PAYETTE] [Translated from French]
A short question on a matter previously raised:
If Senator Ringuette were to issue RinguetteCoin this
week, and if our Chair already had his bitcoin for...
a number of months already, I would like to know what
the value of one in relation to the other would be.
[ANDREAS] The various [crypto]currencies that exist...
are related to each other based on a free-floating
market exchange rate, determined by trade...
between individuals on exchanges where those
currencies can be bought and sold for each other.
This is exactly the same mechanism by
which the exchange rate between the...
Canadian dollar and U.S. dollar is determined.
Or between any currency in the modern world.
All of these currencies have a free-floating market value.
I would argue, if there is very low liquidity in the market,
that it will be very difficult to establish a price...
that is representative of the value of that currency.
Price discovery will be difficult
and lead to very large volatility.
As bitcoin and the other [crypto]currencies
[grow] larger, the volatility decreases, in fact.
The volatility of the bitcoin [price] today is
not at all dissimilar from the volatility of oil...
during the first decade of its discovery
as a substitute fuel instead of whale oil.
We see this with new technologies. As the market
develops, it starts off with tremendous volatility.
But over time, as the amount of volume and liquidity
in the market increases, the volatility is reduced...
until these currencies become extremely stable.
For a global currency, a $5 billion valuation is tiny.
I would expect the bitcoin price will
remain volatile for many years to come.
[HERVIEUX-PAYETTE] [Translated from French]
I think Senator Ringuette can give some thought...
to this $5 billion.
There was another subject that was discussed,
namely the matter of security in the use of bitcoins.
We are parliamentarians here,
doing this study within a parliament.
After this particular committee, I will
be sitting on the finance committee.
I would be interested to know more about the control
that governments might be able to exercise...
if all operations are conducted in bitcoin
and the value is constantly changing.
How would a government be
able to exercise its fiscal power?
[ANDREAS] Well, the citizens of that government
would exercise direct control over the currency...
through their own purchasing decisions.
Through ownership, they would have
control over their own units of currency.
In many cases, as I mentioned
before, Bitcoin is not unregulated.
It is regulated by mathematics as well as dynamic
markets that exist among its participants and users.
The price of bitcoin, its value in commercial
transactions, or whatever use to which it is put,
is managed directly by the end-user,
who are arguably the same constituents.
If the constituents can apply direct
control over currency, they will do so.
[HERVIEUX-PAYETTE] [Translated from French]
My last question, then.
We talked about the value in the month of June.
We will be making our tax returns in April.
What value would we use if we wanted to be
able to make conversions for tax authorities?
Of course, when filing a tax return,
it is necessary to establish a value.
If there is a serious amount of fluctuation...
I realize that the quantities are not high.
There aren't that many taxpayers with huge incomes.
Let's say, the average Canadian earns $45,000 per year.
What value would be attributed to the revenue
from January, February, March, and so forth?
How would it be possible to monitor and control
this type of declaration of income or revenue?
[ANDREAS] That is a very interesting question, an area
where regulatory clarity would be extremely useful.
I earn the vast majority of my income directly in bitcoin.
Since October of last year, I have earned
very little in terms of national currencies.
I get paid in bitcoin, and pay many
of my expenses directly in bitcoin.
For the purposes of taxation, I treat the
bitcoin as earnings in a foreign currency,
just as if I would be doing contract work for
a European company and being paid in euros.
I will assess the market value of the transaction
when I earn the income, at that market price.
Then I will render taxes to the tax
authority in the national currency.
After all, the primary power of the tax authority is
forcing people to pay in the currency of their choice.
What becomes difficult in the use of currency is...
Its classification in the tax code
depends on the use I have for it.
For example, if I use my brokerage account
to purchase euros for investment purposes,
and I sell those euros two months later,
I realize a gain and am subject to capital gains tax.
However, if I visit Paris, use euros to pay for a ticket
to the local Paris Zoo, and the value of the euro...
changes between the moment I purchased [the euros]
with my own currency, and when I pay for the ticket,
I will not assessed for capital gains taxes
because that is considered a currency use.
Therefore, it is treated differently.
[In that instance], the tax code is flexible enough
to allow me to declare the appropriate use...
for tax classification, depending on how I used it.
At the moment, in the United States, there has
been a ruling that bitcoin operates as a commodity...
[subject to] capital gains taxation,
which is the wrong answer in my opinion.
However, if bitcoin had been classified purely as
currency, that would be the wrong answer too.
The correct answer, in my opinion,
should be that it depends on how it is used.
If it is used for investment, then obviously
it is subject to capital gains and losses.
But if it is used for consumer spending, then it
operates as a currency and medium of exchange.
The tax system [should] allow me to
declare how I have used the currency,
and then impose penalties if I have
made that declaration incorrectly.
That is how it works with every other currency.
This is an area where clarity would be extremely useful.
It would allow us to use currencies such as bitcoin...
in the same way that we use [other]
currencies from all over the world.
[HERVIEUX-PAYETTE] Thank you.
[IRVING GERSTEIN] Thank you.
Senator Tkachuk, to be followed by Senator Maltais.
[DAVID TKACHUK] Welcome, Mr. Antonopoulos.
Thank you for your testimony here today.
It has been an interesting afternoon.
The other virtual currencies, are they
based on an algorithm as well?
Is it the same one as used for Bitcoin?
There are several algorithms within Bitcoin.
The central invention is the blockchain and the
security model for consensus through proof-of-work,
which is a [method] that allows a network to arrive
at a secure picture of what the current ledger is...
based on competition.
That central technological innovation, the blockchain,
is used in the vast majority of [crypto]currencies.
I will call that the blockchain invention.
However, there are other algorithms in Bitcoin, such as
the algorithm that determines how [units] are issued,
how often and how much of the currency is issued.
Other currencies have taken different perspectives,
using a different monetary policy recipe.
We have seen the development of a very
broad range of choices, including currencies...
that are inflationary in nature
and have a much bigger supply.
Even currencies that implement a demurrage, meaning
a negative interest rate, to encourage consumption...
and discourages savings.
As a laboratory, these currencies can express a range
of monetary policies and political perspectives.
The underlying invention that secures the entire network
is almost exactly the same across all these currencies.
[DAVID TKACHUK] We have heard in previous
testimony about the miners, the people who issue..
or "mine" the currency.
There were some stories in
the paper in June of this year,
[which said] a company had over 51% of the mining market for bitcoin.
So it was developing like a quasi-monopoly. Can one
company have a total monopoly in issuing bitcoins?
Does that jeopardize the whole currency itself?
Do you have controls on that? How does it all work?
It is important to emphasize that the purpose of
mining is to secure and verify all transactions.
The reward for mining is currency issuance,
which we should not confuse for the main purpose.
Mining is rewarded with currency
issuance for securing the network.
The reward acts as an incentive to
ensure that the network remains secure.
The company in question is a mining organization.
It operates a mining pool, similar to a lottery pool,
which means they didn't control the hashing directly.
They acted as a [facilitator] where many independent
miners could pool their hashing power in order to...
achieve smoother returns on their hardware investment.
When playing the lottery by yourself,
you may win, but on a very irregular schedule.
If you play as part of a pool, you will get more
frequent, but lower, payments in a similar way.
Mining is a competitive function,
individuals do not fare [as well].
Their payments [are irregular].
Instead, they pull their actions together.
Interestingly, when GHash.IO approached --
but did not reach -- 51%, and [controlled above 40%],
this led to a market response where individual miners
recognized the potential risk to the reputation...
of the network.
Although, I don't believe it was a serious technical risk.
They withdrew their mining capacity from that pool
operator and redirected it to other pool operators.
Shortly thereafter, GHash.IO had their cumulative
mining power drop to slightly below 30%.
[This behaviour] provides a very good level
of protection against individualized attacks.
That is a very big amount, but at the same time,
it is not big enough to provide a monopoly.
On a technical note, a mining pool or individual
miner achieving the majority of the [hashpower]...
can potentially disrupt the transaction processing
function of the network, for a short term.
However, they cannot steal funds from any of the users,
re-direct funds from any of the [transactions].
and they cannot invalidate transactions.
They can only delay the processing. It is not
as big of a risk as most people believe it is.
Because of the market mechanisms behind it, we see
again and again that it is a self-correcting system.
[DAVID TKACHUK] Just so I can understand
whether it is a method of exchange or a currency...
If I have yen in Canada, I can't really buy anything.
I must go to a bank and exchange it for [dollars].
No one takes [yen here]. I must go exchange it
for Canadian dollars so I can buy something.
It is the same in each country. And in each country,
those [Canadian] dollars will have certain value.
Even though my Canadian dollar trades up and down
compared to the U.S. dollar, as does everything else,
I still deal in Canadian dollars.
It basically stays the same for Canadian products,
unless it depends heavily on imports.
Does the virtual sphere itself have its own stability?
In other words, when something is priced in
Europe for one bitcoin and I have one bitcoin,
can I still buy that for one bitcoin even though...
the value of that bitcoin has changed in relation to
the currency of my country, or the American dollar?
[ANDREAS] The exchange rates between
bitcoin and individual currencies such as...
the euro, Canadian dollars, U.S. dollars, etc.
has sufficient liquidity that arbitrage is
possible between the various exchanges.
This means the purchasing power of one bitcoin
is the same no matter what the national currency.
The fluctuations are minuscule because...
with any serious fluctuation, if I could
buy bitcoin cheaper for Canadian dollars,
then sell it more expensively for U.S. dollars,
that creates an immediate opportunity
for arbitrage between the two markets.
That's exactly what is happening. In many cases,
arbitrage in bitcoin is even more effective because...
the bitcoin can be transferred between exchanges
almost instantaneously and across borders.
In traditional financial markets, moving
money like that takes [quite] a bit longer.
The differences between national
currencies even out very quickly.
There are [few] fluctuations there.
My bitcoin purchasing power, while volatile overall,
is the same across any national currency.
[DAVID TKACHUK] Can you see a time- Is that
where we are heading, where people internationally...
price things in bitcoins?
Things will be bought and sold in bitcoins, no matter
what is happening underneath to national currencies?
[Maybe] because you save so much
money in exchange, and all the rest of it.
Is that where we are going,
is that where we are heading?
[ANDREAS] In the long-term, I believe bitcoin will be
stable enough in terms of volatility that it will be...
possible to price things directly in bitcoin.
At that moment, bitcoin [would] become a universal
currency in terms of its utility across the internet.
At least on the internet, that would make it
extremely competitive against national currencies,
both in terms of ease-of-use and flexibility.
I would expect that to happen. However, I think we are
several years away from the volatility [going down]...
[enough] such that things
can be priced directly in bitcoin.
[DAVID TKACHUK] Okay.
Could I have time for one more question?
Bitcoin can be stored.
[For example], Senator Gerstein. I don't know where
he keeps his bitcoin. Where does he keep this bitcoin?
Do you keep it in your own wallet?
Is it a virtual wallet where you keep your bitcoins?
You can do that?
[ANDREAS] This may be a tiny bit too technical,
but I'll provide you with some some insight anyway.
The bitcoin are actually not stored by individuals.
They are stored on the network, on the public ledger.
The public ledger knows who has [owns] what bitcoin.
What Senator Gerstein has are the keys
which allow him to sign for transactions,
essentially signatory control over those funds.
[DAVID TKACHUK] The keys unlock it?
[ANDREAS] To unlock them.
How you store the keys, depends.
There are many ways to store the keys.
Effectively, they are just numbers. [To protect my keys],
I actually print those out on pieces of paper,
and put them in a physical medium.
I also have keys that control smaller amounts of bitcoin,
spending change if you like, on my mobile phone.
I have some on my desktop. I have some
on hardware devices that I am trying out.
But the vast majority [of the keys] are
printed out as physical [paper] copies.
It is more secure. Those can't be hacked [remotely].
You would need to break into my house.
[DAVID TKACHUK] Companies, businesses will do
multiple transactions, thousands or millions per day.
Can bitcoin adapt to that? Can you do payroll for a two
hundred, five hundred, a thousand people with bitcoin?
With deductions and all the rest of it? Or is it an issue?
[ANDREAS] Not only can you do that...
[DAVID TKACHUK] People are doing it?
[ANDREAS] A medium skilled programmer...
can do that with a few hundred lines of code,
like in Python, accessing the [company wallet]...
and instructing it to do that, which is fascinating.
Not only that, but they could do it for transactions to a
thousand people living in a hundred different countries,
which is almost impossible to do with today's money.
So if you try to do payroll- There are many companies
in the technology space [with that problem].
For example, Google pays tens of thousands
of affiliate companies for advertising revenue.
The cost for them to pay these companies
that ad revenue across the world is enormous.
The possibility of automating that and using a single
currency for electronic payments, it can be done.
It can be done extremely fast, efficiently and globally.
[DAVID TKACHUK] I like "cheaply," too.
[ANDREAS] And very cheaply.
[IRVING GERSTEIN] Senator Maltais, please.
[GHISLAIN MALTAIS] [Translated from French]
Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
First a short comment and then some questions.
I agree with my colleague, Senator Campbell,
when he said that people of a certain age might...
have some trouble trying this out.
We did have a machine and Chair generously bought
$100 worth of bitcoin. He never told us about it.
I don't know what has become of it, whether there has
been a loss, but of course that is not your problem.
You said that a user of bitcoin might be able
to predict the monetary supply in the future.
For example, a user of bitcoin such as the Chair [could]
predict what the monetary supply will be in 30 years.
It seems to me that the Minister of Finance probably
should have made use of this for the next five years.
It certainly seems to me that if you are able to
tell what the monetary supply will be in 30 years,
then this is a very useful knowledge.
[ANDREAS] Because Bitcoin is designed to simulate
the extraction of precious metals in its progression,
it is entirely possible to predict, with very high accuracy,
exactly how much currency will be available
on the market at a specific period of time.
That doesn't necessarily mean that supply will
meet the demand, or that it is the correct supply.
We just know what that supply will be.
Today, we can predict to a very high degree of accuracy
what the supply of gold will be over the next year.
It has been extracted at a very predictable rate.
It works similarly with bitcoin.
[GHISLAIN MALTAIS] On that particular point,
I think any insurance company actuary,
when they establish an annuity over a period of 30 years,
are able to make a good prediction for the figures...
that will probably turn out to be quite realistic.
So they don't need Bitcoin in order to establish
what the money supply will be in 30 years.
They are able to make an extrapolation.
It is a very simple mathematical formula.
This can be done by an actuary.
But there is a question that I find quite puzzling.
Do you think that the Bitcoin system would
be a duplicate of the present banking system?
The banks are able to adapt
to any type of new technology.
The World Bank, when it comes to capital, are
probably investing more in technological research...
on digital currency than Bitcoin could ever be.
[ANDREAS] Bitcoin, or rather the invention
behind Bitcoin, the blockchain technology,
is an invention that will have a substantial
influence over the future of banking.
I have had several discussions with banks that
are very interested in using similar systems...
in order to create more efficient
networks within the banking system.
For example, clearing operations such as those for
world-wide fund transfer, stock and equity purchases,
are handled by intermediaries.
Bitcoin would allow banks to handle those...
in a decentralized network by simulating the
same technology as Bitcoin on their own.
Furthermore, banks in the developing world are
very interested in using bitcoin to extend services...
to areas where they can't deploy infrastructure.
Very similarly, at first telecommunications companies
were somewhat threatened by the internet,
but now run their networks on top of the internet.
Banks will eventually find ways to utilize this technology.
I would not be surprised if big parts of financial
services systems eventually run on top of technology...
very similar to Bitcoin, perhaps Bitcoin itself.
[GHISLAIN MALTAIS] This leads me to ask you, then...
Do you not have the impression that you were
swallowed up before you even came into existence?
The banks will never ever let you
have so much operating [room].
I'm not just talking about Canadian or American
banks, I'm talking about banks in all the world.
I don't think that the banks will
let this go by without reacting.
I realize that this is quite successful.
Young people are very enthused about it, but I don't
think banks will let themselves be dispossessed.
Bitcoin is not a solid organization;
for the time being, it is simply a virtual one.
[ANDREAS] I remember the exact same discussion...
when the idea [was put forth that] the international
telecommunications union would be thwarted...
or even somehow threatened by this
nascent technology called the internet.
That idea [seemed] ridiculous on its face; the idea
that states would allow the internet to give people...
freedom of expression was preposterous.
The idea that the internet would be allowed
to subvert the will of despots around the world,
and would not be instantly shut down whenever
they felt it was threatening their authority,
was preposterous.
And yet, all of these things have happened.
I believe that Bitcoin empowers individuals, especially
individuals who do not even have access to banking.
It will create a thriving economy of its own,
an economy that will not threaten banks,
but will open new opportunities for banks.
In the end, just like the telecommunication companies,
many of their old models and old profit
sources will be fundamentally disrupted.
Today, AT&T's long-distance network has been
decimated. Skype has dominated that space.
Yet AT&T did not give up. They became one of
the world's largest internet service providers.
Eventually, I believe that bitcoin [and bitcoin-like]
currencies will decimate certain industries,
especially high-profit, low-service industries such as
remittances, which are exploitative in their nature.
They will open up new industries,
new products, and new services.
Economic activity enabled by bringing together billions
of people on a fully connected, global financial system.
[The benefits] will be so much bigger than the potential
risk this may pose to the profits of incumbents.
[GHISLAIN MALTAIS] Thank you.
[IRVING GERSTEIN] This concludes round one.
We will enter into round two. I have Senator Black,
Senator Massicotte, and Senator Greene on my list.
Before turning it over to Senator Black...
In your comments -- which have been fascinating --
you made reference to one of the great motivators...
for you personally [becoming] involved in this,
is the technology that will bring [financial services]
to people who don't have it today, using the
[line] "empowering billions around the world."
If I am correct, I believe Mr. Gates, in his charitable giving
in Africa, makes use of a digital currency called M-Pesa.
Could you just expand a little on what impact bitcoin,
M-Pesa, digital currency in general, will have on Africa?
[ANDREAS] Absolutely. M-Pesa is a fascinating study
for those of us who are interested in digital currencies.
It has shown what is possible when low-friction
digital money is introduced into an environment...
without the need for massive infrastructure.
An environment that doesn't have
well-developed banking services.
M-Pesa was started as an experiment...
that allowed individuals to transfer cellphone
minutes amongst themselves and their families,
through a telecom provider in Kenya.
I Imagine the moment this became a
currency was a very mundane moment.
Maybe a customer arrived at a store and realized they
didn't have sufficient money to buy a dozen eggs.
Then asking, "Well, can I give you
a couple of cellphone minutes instead?"
With that simple concept, a currency is born.
What's fascinating about M-Pesa is, we roll forward
just twelve years and M-Pesa is now responsible for...
40% of the GDP of Kenya, a staggering amount.
It represents the adoption of what was [previously] a
largely underground, cash-based, illiquid economy...
that was very slow to operate, and turbocharging that
by providing enormous liquidity and fluidity...
into the economic system.
At the moment, Bitcoin is not ready to be adopted
easily on the most deployed platform in the world,
which is a feature phone,
the Nokia 1000, of which there exist billions.
It requires a bit more infrastructure than that,
but gradually we see two trends converging:
First, bitcoin is being applied on
simpler and simpler technology.
We already see its use through SMS text messaging.
Second, the collapse in the cost of producing smart
phones, with the Android approaching about $25.
There are already applications in the Bitcoin space
that would allow a single Android phone to support...
thousands of simple SMS customers
by giving them bitcoin wallets.
That would allow a young kid in Lagos, Nigeria to
buy an Android smartphone and become a bank...
serving thousands of customers, giving them access
to the equivalent of a Western Union terminal,
a credit facility for buying loans, as well as
a trading facility for all of the world's markets.
This could be run off a simple Android
smartphone and SMS feature phones.
M-Pesa showed us that it is possible;
Bitcoin makes that phenomenon global.
in talking about the unbanked, the World Bank estimates
that 2.5 billion people are completely unbanked,
living in cash-based societies.
However, that vastly underestimates the problem.
If you [compare with] the types of banking
facilities that we have in the western world,
the ability I have to access a brokerage account
[and pick from] any of the international markets,
to convert any currency I want without controls,
transmit money to any country in the world I want,
and to use it as a simple consumer...
[That experience] is very far removed
from what most people have.
If you look at the unbanked as those who have a single
currency, closed account that doesn't have access...
to international markets, credit, or trading capabilities,
more than six billion people in the
world live with that kind of banking.
Two and a half billion are completely unbanked.
Bitcoin can change that environment dramatically,
in less than a decade.
[IRVING GERSTEIN] Thank you.
Senator Black, to be followed by Senator Massicotte.
[DOUGLAS BLACK] Thank you very much,
Mr. Chairman. I would just like to thank you,
again, for this contribution. It is extremely helpful.
I want to move to a couple of final points
that I want to have clear in my mind.
I want to take, from your comments,
arising from what Senator Ringuette asked...
Through this hearing, we have been exploring
the opportunity that may exist for Canada,
for innovation if we get this right.
Can you succinctly tell us what
you think that opportunity is?
[ANDREAS] Well, I think there are two aspects.
One is the pure research and technology innovation
capabilities that might exist in the Bitcoin sphere.
I like to emphasize is that bitcoin
is not just money for the internet.
To look at it simply as money for
the internet, is to miss the point.
Bitcoin is the internet of money.
Currency is just the first application.
Currency is an app running on a decentralized
trust network based on blockchain technology,
which means many other apps will exist.
The bitcoin currency is almost the same as email
was in the '90s. It enabled the growth of the internet.
It was the killer application that made it viable
and worthwhile for people to get involved,
but it couldn't possibly open our eyes to the
endless possibilities which came afterwards.
The web, we couldn't envision that in the
early '90s, or even Facebook and Twitter.
Bitcoin the currency is just the tip of the iceberg.
It is the proto-technology that will bring
this decentralized network to consumers.
But there will be other apps, and it is
already evolving at a tremendous rate.
From a pure research and innovation
perspective, I think it is incredible.
The other is to think about the possibilities
of extending banking services [to new areas].
Even though Canada has a highly banked population,
there are still pockets within this country.
I know that in the U.S., close to 18% of the population
have no or very limited banking capabilities.
That is probably true of most developed nations.
There are pockets within this country where
people have very little access to banks.
I think the combination of doing primary research
and innovation in these new technologies,
and opening banking to reach different corners of
this country, disadvantaged parts of the population....
That is a very potent combination, especially if we take
advantage of the international aspects of this currency.
[DOUGLAS BLACK] Thank you very much.
One last question, if I may, Mr. Chairman.
How did New York State get it wrong?
[ANDREAS] I think they got it wrong in many ways.
First of all, by rushing to regulate very soon.
More importantly, by regulating Bitcoin in exactly the
same way that the banking system currently operates,
failing to see the distinctions between
Bitcoin and the current system.
The only analogy I can think of... if in proto-internet
stage, the Federal Communications Commmission...
in the United States had decided the internet was simply
a sophisticated form of citizens band (CB) radio...
and required a license for every website operator.
Such an outcome would have almost certainly
destroyed the internet industry in the United States.
However, because of the enormous need for such a tool,
it would not have affected the
internet industry everywhere else.
It would have simply pushed that innovation elsewhere.
I think treating bitcoin as a proto-bank account
with some fancy features is missing the point;
to regulate it as such would completely stifle it,
put it into the playing field of incumbents.
It ties up [Bitcoin companies]
in the same kinds of regulations.
It would force them to behave more like a bank,
when its unique characteristic is, it isn't a bank.
[DOUGLAS BLACK] Thank you very much.
Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
[IRVING GERSTEIN] Thank you. Senator Massicotte,
to be followed by Senator Greene.
[PAUL MASSICOTTE] Thank you again.
One technical question, then a more important question.
On a technical side, many countries and provinces...
have sales tax and a couple have income tax.
For the merchants using your currency,
is there software [for that] already in place?
I know from a dollar sense, cash registers
have become pretty sophisticated so that it is...
easy for them do the accounting to collect the sales tax.
[PAUL MASSICOTTE] Does that already exist?
[ANDREAS] Absolutely. In fact, it is easier with bitcoin.
The public ledger provides a complete
record of all of the transactions,
as if all of my bank statements from
the first moment I used bitcoin are online.
I rendered sales tax to the state of California for
the business I ran, selling products via bitcoin.
I also pay my income taxes in U.S. dollars,
based on my income which is entirely in bitcoin.
I do all of my accounting using
traditional accounting software.
[PAUL MASSICOTTE] And the software is in place
to do the transfers and calculations immediately?
[ANDREAS] Yes, although it is rather cumbersome
at the moment. The modularities are quite different.
For example, in traditional banking I have
a handful of four or five different accounts.
In bitcoin, I have well over two thousand "accounts."
With bitcoin it makes sense to create
a new account for every transaction.
Though they are not really an "account." Therefore,
if you try to put it into the same model, it is difficult.
However, the software is being developed.
[PAUL MASSICOTTE] Let me talk to you about-
You basically answered the question, but...
The way I see it, this is a highly secure
form of anonymous transfer for property.
You can call it currency, but you are using it now
for a currency from a sense of bartering.
I presume, it seems to me that this could be very useful
in many things, including exchange of [other] property.
Today, we have a bunch of lawyers or notaries who
acknowledge the safe transfer of real-estate property.
But it seems to me this application could
be used very often in many different facets.
So let's [look] five years [ahead]. How do you see this
technology being used to the benefit of our society?
Give me some examples.
[ANDREAS] There are some very interesting
applications where the decentralized ledger...
is used as a public record, of sorts,
for all kinds of [information].
From registering bicycles,
to automobiles, to company shares.
Two days ago, I was at a Bitcoin conference where
a couple was married, and had their marriage...
registered on the blockchain for the first time.
They used the blockchain as a register of that contract.
You could use it to register titles and deeds for property,
and transfer those titles and deeds for any form
of property, including vehicles and real-estate.
With a simple electronic transaction,
you could transfer the deed to a car.
Even better and more importantly, the car could look up
its own title and render itself usable to the new owner.
Automatically. This concept is called "smart property,"
where the property recognizes its ownership
through reference to the blockchain.
All forms of decentralized registration
can be implemented with the blockchain.
Furthermore, you can issue share certificates or
any other form of token, which can then be traded.
Sharing my bandwidth and receiving a token in return,
which I can spend to use someone else's bandwidth,
creating the possibilities for [more] sharing economy
[services], similar to how we have AirBnb or Uber today.
We can do many of those things using digital tokens.
There is a company here in Toronto that
developed an application that allows you --
upon submitting a transaction on the blockchain
-- to unlock a door for an AirBnb apartment.
Your smartphone would make the payment
and then unlock the door to the apartment,
and have access to that property.
[PAUL MASSICOTTE] It is amazing.
A minor or secondary question...
I don't understand why they used the
blockchain for a couple getting married.
Is he scared to get mixed up with the wife?
[Laughter] What is the issue?
[ANDREAS] So, it was largely symbolic and
a proof-of-concept. This couple was already married...
under traditional state laws.
However, they wanted a record of their marriage that
was publicly accessible, unforgeable, unchangeable.
It provides a permanent record of what has happened,
a history that is unalterable by anyone within an hour.
and will be preserved through time.
[PAUL MASSICOTTE] So the bedroom door
does not open if it is the wrong person? [Laughter]
Automatic accessing. [Laughter]
[IRVING GERSTEIN] Our concluding
question from Senator Greene, please.
[STEPHEN GREENE] Thank you very much.
I take your point about the dangers of
inappropriate or premature regulation.
We don't know where this is heading,
and the pace of change is [fast].
I don't think we want to influence the
pace of change or what it might lead to.
We must write a report which
will have recommendations.
My question is, what would your reaction be
to a report with just one recommendation,
and that recommendation would be,
'there should be no regulations [at this time],'
but we will re-visit this in five years?
[ANDREAS] I think that would be a very good idea.
I think there is some room for clarification.
For example, the tax status for individuals.
Or at least clarifying the right of an individual to make
a choice in the currency they use as a consumer,
and to affirm the legality of using digital
currencies in all forms of commerce...
as entirely equivalent with any other national currency.
Recognizing it is a private
form of barter and transaction.
Recognizing the corresponding principles,
which I consider neutral principles, but they are also...
principles of the Enlightenment: freedom of association,
freedom of expression and conscience.
I think removing ambiguity in that particular arena,
for personal use, would be enormously useful.
[STEPHEN GREENE] I agree, thank you very much.
[IRVING GERSTEIN] Mr. Antonopoulos,
your reputation preceded your arrival,
You may recall that in my introductory remarks,
I did not introduce you as 'a' Bitcoin guru.
but as the Bitcoin guru.
[ANDREAS] You humble me, Senator.
[IRVING GERSTEIN] I think I could speak...
on behalf of all members of the committee in saying
that you have more than lived up to that reputation.
And we greatly appreciate- [Applause]
Thank you very much. This meeting is concluded.
[Music]