[SAM DASTYARI] Open the second hearing of the Senate
Economics References Committee into digital currency.
The Senate referred this inquiry to the Committee
on 2 October 2014, for report by 2 March 2015.
On 2 March 2015, the Senate granted
an extension to report by 10 August 2015.
The Committee has received forty-six submissions,
which are available on the Committee's website.
I would like to take this opportunity to thank
those who made submissions to the inquiry,
and the witnesses who have taken time
to appear before the committee today,
and at the previous public
hearing on 26 November 2014.
These are public proceedings, although
the committee may determine or agree to...
a request that evidence be heard in camera.
I ask everyone to ensure that they have switched off,
or turned to silent [mode], their mobile phones.
I would ask photographers and cameramen to
follow the instructions of the Committee Secretary...
and ensure that senators' and witnesses'
laptops and personal papers are not filmed.
I remind all witnesses that,
in giving evidence to the Committee, they
are protected by parliamentary privilege.
It is unlawful for anyone to threaten or disadvantage
a witness on account of evidence given to a committee,
and such actions may be treated
by the Senate as contempt.
If a witness objects to answering a question,
the witness should state the ground
upon which the objection is taken.
The Committee will determine whether
it will insist on an answer, having regard to...
the ground on which it was claimed.
If the Committee determines to insist on an answer,
a witness may request that
the answer is given in camera.
Such a request may of course
be made at any other time.
A witness called to answer a question for the first time...
should state their full name and
the capacity in which they appear.
I now welcome Mr. [Andreas] Antonopoulos.
For the record, could you state your full name
and the capacity in which you appear?
[ANDREAS] Hello, my name
is Andreas M. Antonopoulos.
I am an author and computer security expert.
[SAM DASTYARI] Thank you so much, and thank you
for taking the extra effort to participate in our inquiry.
I want to invite you to make a few brief opening remarks,
and then I think we have a few questions for you.
[ANDREAS] Thank you.
Thank you, Chair and Committee members.
I appreciate this opportunity to contribute
to these proceedings about digital currency.
My [professional] experience is primarily in
information security and network architecture.
I have a master's degree in networks and distributed
systems, and have worked in this field since 1992.
I spent twenty years working on networks and
data centers for financial services companies...
before I found Bitcoin in late 2011.
I have been working full-time in the
Bitcoin space for the past two years,
and written a book for software developers
with the title "Mastering Bitcoin."
Bitcoin's unique architecture and payment mechanism
has important implications for network access,
innovation, privacy, individual empowerment,
consumer protection, and regulation.
I welcome the opportunity to talk
to you about these issues today.
For Australia, Bitcoin represents
a unique opportunity in two areas:
firstly, Bitcoin can introduce much-needed
competition in the retail payments industry,
undercutting the expensive systems
offered by credit and debit cards,
while significantly improving
security and privacy for consumers;
secondly, the Bitcoin industry can establish Australia
on the forefront of the next wave of innovation...
that can extend financial services to more than
two billion people throughout Southeast Asia...
who are currently underbanked.
Just like cellular telephones allowed billions
[of people] to become connected with the world,
entirely bypassing the need for fixed-line telephone
infrastructure, Bitcoin can do the same for banking.
Australia is already the home
of a thriving Bitcoin industry,
which can become a leader in the region and the world.
Until the invention of Bitcoin in 2008, security and
decentralization seemed like [opposing] concepts.
Traditional models for financial payment networks and
banking rely on centralized control to provide security.
The architecture is built around central
authorities such as a clearinghouse.
Those within the center of the network are vested
with enormous power, act with full authority;
therefore, they must be very carefully vetted,
regulated, and subject to oversight.
Bitcoin is fundamentally different. The security
model of blockchain currencies is decentralized.
There is no centre to the network, no central authority,
no concentration of power, and no actor in whom...
complete trust must be vested.
In Bitcoin, security is an emergent property of the
collaboration of thousands of network participants,
not a function of a single authority.
If a bad actor infiltrates a traditional financial network,
the network itself and all its participants are at risk.
In contrast, if a bad actor has accessed the Bitcoin
network, they have no power over the network itself.
They do not compromise trust in the network.
Therefore, the Bitcoin network can be
open to any participant without vetting,
authentication, identification, or prior authorization.
This freedom of access creates freedom to innovate
without permission from the incumbents,
the same fundamental force that has driven
innovation on the internet for twenty years,
creating enormous value for all.
Centralized financial networks can
never be fully open to innovation...
because their security depends on access control.
Incumbents in such networks effectively utilize access
control to stifle outside innovation and competition,
falsely presenting their anti-competitive
actions as consumer protection.
Bitcoin's decentralized nature affords consumer
protection in the most powerful and direct way,
by allowing bitcoin users direct control over
the privacy of their financial transactions.
Bitcoin transactions never expose
vulnerable account identifiers.
Bitcoin users can protect the privacy
of their transactions without relying on,
or trusting any intermediaries.
Contrary to popular misconception,
Bitcoin is not unregulated.
Rather, several aspects of the
Bitcoin network and financial system...
are regulated by mathematical algorithms.
The algorithmic regulation in Bitcoin offers
predictable, objective, measurable outcomes.
Algorithmic regulation provides certainty
without nationalistic or geopolitical influence.
In a time of unprecedented currency wars,
mathematical neutrality is a safe haven.
In trying to understand consumer protection,
[roles for] oversight, audit, and regulation of Bitcoin,
there is a risk that many will try to apply familiar models
of the past to this new digital currency system.
I urge you to resist the temptation to apply
centralized solutions to this decentralized network.
Centralizing Bitcoin [would] weaken its security, dull its
innovative potential, and remove its most disruptive...
yet also most promising features.
Centralization will disempower users
while empowering incumbents.
Consumer protection will not be achieved by
removing Bitcoin's built-in privacy characteristics.
We cannot protect consumers by removing
their ability to control their own privacy,
then asking them to entrust it in the same intermediaries
who have failed them so many times before.
In this new decentralized financial network, we have
the opportunity to invent new security mechanisms...
based upon innovations such as multi-signature
escrow, smart contracts, hardware wallets,
decentralized audits, and algorithmic proof of reserves.
These are the new decentralized regulatory
and security tools that are most appropriate...
for a decentralized digital currency.
Thank you for the opportunity
to address this committee.
[SAM DASTYARI] Thank you so much
for that fantastic opening statement.
I have a few questions. Before I get to them,
I think Senator Canavan had a few. Senator Canavan?
[MATTHEW CANAVAN] Thank you, Chair. I want to
thank Mr. Antonopoulos for making yourself available.
We were recently in Canada and I know you
have given evidence to their Senate Committee.
They mentioned you as somebody who was one
of the most impressive witnesses they have had.
It is fantastic that you have been able to join us as well.
I really want to drill down on your last comment there,
about avoiding imposing old-school regulatory models,
so to speak, on a newly emerging technology.
How do we draw the line? I have noticed in
some of the other comments you have made...
that there is a distinction between the use of
bitcoin between individuals on a personal basis,
and perhaps some of the infrastructure that might
grow around Bitcoin, including custodial accounts...
[and other] banking-type services.
Do you still see that there is some regulation needed
for Bitcoin companies that might provide more...
than just access to currency?
[ANDREAS] Thank you, Senator. Custodial accounts,
as you mentioned, are of particular concern.
In fact, any accounts that take control of
[many] bitcoin keys remove them from...
the protection [of the] security [model] of a
[decentralized] network, create areas of centralization.
We have seen before, many times, that such
environments are prone to hacking, theft,
and [even] cases [where] we suspect there
to have been embezzlement and insider action.
Those types of organizations with
custodial access have all the problems...
of traditional, centralized financial networks.
In short, if you give someone your money,
they will [try to] run away with it.
The need for regulation, oversight, audits,
and all the traditional financial controls
imposed in those situations, is paramount.
The key is to recognize the fundamental difference
between custodial [and non-custodial] accounts...
in decentralized access and control over
finance that Bitcoin offers in its model.
[MATTHEW CANAVAN] So, say in your situation..
I presume you are more familiar
with Canada than [Australia].
In Canada, would you think it is possible to
apply the prudential consumer protection laws...
that exist for traditional banks to Bitcoin and digital
currency-type banks, without major modification?
Could they be brought into your financial regulatory
space quite easily? And treated just like they are-
You know, they must have reserves against liabilities and
deposits, provide consumers with product disclosure...
and all those aspects.
Could that happen? Could we do that easily?
[ANDREAS] I am more familiar with the
regulatory framework in the United States.
[MATTHEW CANAVAN] Yes, that's fine. Okay.
I would say that many of the existing regulations
[there] apply quite comfortably to Bitcoin.
[Custodial accounts] can be treated similarly
to any foreign currency [in a] brokerage account,
with all the requirements which come from the
use of that type of instrument and account system.
However, there are some unique [operations]
that can be done in the Bitcoin space...
that can't be done in traditional financial environments.
I think there is an opportunity to
take advantage of those [niches].
For example, in a traditional financial institution, internal
audits and third-party audits must be used in order to...
prove reserve adequacy.
That is subject to manipulation and can be
falsified if the auditors are not eagle-eyed.
We have seen several scandals,
especially in the United States,
where auditors were complicit
with financial shenanigans,
leading to falsified audit accounts.
In Bitcoin, mathematical proofs of reserve can be
created whereby the reserve accounts of bitcoin...
[attributed to] each and every participant
who has a custodial account on the service..
can be added up and the result verified independently
by each customer, without revealing anyone's balance.
There are some unique cryptographic solutions that are
innovative and would allow for much more flexibility.
[MATTHEW CANAVAN] At the moment in
the United States, do you see companies...
offering fractional reserve banking for bitcoin?
[ANDREAS] I hope not.
I believe that most of the [services] we see
in the United States are not fractional reserve.
They are full-reserve situations. In Bitcoin, there is a very
high risk with [running] fractional reserve arrangements.
Because of the fixed nature of the currency,
the [price] volatility and exchange rate risk,
such a scheme would be very dangerous.
The problem is whether these organizations
can prove that they have full reserves or not.
That is a question still not answered
to the satisfaction of most consumers.
The other thing to note, very briefly,
is the potential existence of hybrid models.
[These would be] accounts which appear
on the surface to be custodial, but where...
the exchange, bank, or financial institution...
only has control over a minority of
the keys in a multi-signature [setup].
[For example], a financial institution
that has one key out of three keys...
can [partially] authorize a transaction and
sign for it, but cannot [fully] do so on their own.
They [would] need a second signature from another key.
Those hybrid environments require special
consideration, because they offer the flexibility...
of managed banking and financial services
without the risks of custodial control.
Quite simply, the bank can't run away with the money.
[MATTHEW CANAVAN] My final question on
this topic: in the North American Bitcoin industry,
are they calling for, or do they want to have,
your financial regulators [exercise] oversight on them?
Do they want that third-party
assurance from the government?
I forgot the name of your commission
there in America... Sorry? The SEC.
Do they want the SEC to come and give them
a stamp of approval, so they can go to market?
[ANDREAS] Some companies are asking for regulation
and oversight in order to provide [some] certainty.
However, in the United States, one of the reasons
this is such a challenging environment to operate in,
is the overlap between federal,
state, and local regulations.
Money transmitter licenses are regulated at
the state level, which exposes companies to...
fifty different licensing requirements in fifty states.
Between the SEC, Financial Crime Enforcement Network
(FinCEN), the Departments of Justice and the Treasury,
state regulators, banking institutions,
FINRA, and various other organizations,
there are probably two dozen different regulators,
all jumping in and trying to regulate [this industry],
[while] not understanding Bitcoin.
At the moment, one of the big problems [in the United
States] is fragmentation and overlapping of jurisdiction.
That is why jurisdictions that can offer more clarity
in regulator affairs, less of a quilted environment,
will actually have an advantage over the United States.
[MATTHEW CANAVAN] If I can just ask one follow-up:
do you think Australia has that potential advantage?
[ANDREAS] I would have said 'yes' several months ago.
However, I believe that a recent decision applied
a sales tax to every bitcoin purchase or sale,
which I think fundamentally misunderstands the nature
of the system and ascribes properties of a commodity,
which [bitcoin is not.
As a result, that adds significant friction and may be a
major disadvantage for Australian Bitcoin companies.
[MATTHEW CANAVAN] I will leave it there,
Chair, in light of my follow-up. I will hand back.
[SAM DASTYARI] Yes. Mr. Antonopoulos,
so far as we have conducted these hearings-
We had a group of people from the industry come
speak to us about potential opportunities and growth.
After we hear from you, we will have the Australian
security agencies [come in], our equivalent of the FBI,
[consisting of] the Australian federal police,
attorney general's department, and crime commission.
They seem to regularly cite an FBI
report that I think was done in 2011,
regarding security concerns about Bitcoin.
Before they come in, I wouldn't mind having
your take on those kinds of security concerns.
Obviously they will come in and present the
view of the security risks associated with it.
I wouldn't mind getting your take on that.
I know it is not the area you have specialized in,
but I wouldn't mind picking your brain about
how legitimate some of those concerns are,
and how much of them are overblown?
[ANDREAS] Could you be more specific
about which security concerns you refer to?
I am not sure if I am familiar with a specific FBI report.
[SAM DASTYARI] Largely, the concern expressed-
I am paraphrasing the words of others
from the security agencies here.
Effectively, [the concern is] that this is something which
will be used for dark and horrible things on the internet,
drug trafficking and terrorism financing.
That the lack of controls that they have,
as opposed to other currency exchanges,
means that there are greater risks
associated with it than other matters.
As a result, I think there is a hesitation from the
security agencies, about creating a framework...
where this industry can grow.
[ANDREAS] Very good.
Well, that argument in my mind is false.
I will give a number of reasons why I believe it is false.
First of all, it is an argument we have heard before.
We have heard it extensively about the internet itself.
In the early '90s, the internet was seen as a
den of pornographers, thieves, and terrorists.
There were all kinds of horrible stories
about how the future would unfold.
The truth was, it gained adoption by reflecting
the desires and needs of mainstream society.
Most people are more interested in posting videos of
their cats than using it to communicate with terrorists.
The truth is, people will use bitcoin to feed their families,
send their kids to school, pay for healthcare, get payroll..
They will do so because, as it goes mainstream,
so do the use [cases] of this currency.
The currency itself is inherently neutral.
I think there is also a massive misconception about
Bitcoin being anonymous. Bitcoin is not anonymous.
What it doesn't offer is a totalitarian model of
financial surveillance where every transaction...
can be tracked from origin to destination [and
attributed to identities] without due process,
without [suspicion of crime], treating everyone as
[potentially] guilty by engaging in financial transactions.
We have seen in specific prosecutions,
especially here in the United States,
that when [reasonable] calls for concern or
suspicion exist and due process is followed,
the Bitcoin ledger actually offers a forensically
accurate registry of every transaction that happens.
This has been used very effectively by law enforcement.
Traditional law enforcement practices, such as
using informants and constructing trails...
by collecting information through
due process and warrants,
are much more effective in the Bitcoin environment.
For example, for a transaction in the traditional financial
networks that involves a multi-party conspiracy,
in many cases that will [take the form of]
wire transfers across multiple jurisdictions.
Collecting a forensically accurate trail of
these [transfers] requires serving subpoenas...
in multiple jurisdictions, with the collaboration
of Interpol and related agencies.
In Bitcoin, just download the blockchain onto your laptop
and now you have a forensic trail of every transaction...
that has ever happened.
All you need is one thread to pull through due process,
to be able to link [those transactions] to an identity,
You will be able to see a full list of all transactions.
Law enforcement had no problem using those
techniques to deliver prosecutions in the United States,
using [the Bitcoin blockchain] as evidence.
I think these fears are very overrated.
When I speak to law enforcement agents, they think
that Bitcoin is a rather benign form of digital currency.
There are others that are much stealthier and anonymous, which may be encouraged to grow...
if onerous legislation is passed.
Certainly, bitcoin has been used
for criminal purposes. That is a fact.
But if I may use a slightly humorous analogy,
it has come to my attention that the
vast majority of criminals also use shoes.
That doesn't mean that shoes are the problem, right?
Bitcoin is money, which is a means to an end.
The end to which it is put, depends on who is using it.
As it becomes more mainstream, that use will
gradually change and become more benign.
It is natural that, in an environment where cash is used
for the majority of [lower level] criminal enterprise,
a form of digital cash which offers lower
friction will be attractive to certain elements.
But if they make the mistake of thinking it is
anonymous, they will find out soon that it is not.
Bitcoin is resistant to totalitarian surveillance.
I think that is a good thing in a democratic society.
[MATTHEW CANAVAN] I'm just trying to square that.
You say it is resistant to totalitarian surveillance,
but you can download the entire
blockchain onto your laptop now.
I don't understand all the cryptography behind this, but
presumably governments will employ smart people...
who could find a way to still surveil our transactions
if we were all using digital currencies.
Is that not a risk, given that they are all public?
[ANDREAS] Certainly the transactions can be surveilled,
but they cannot be [easily] attached to identities.
In most cases, in order to attach it to an identity,
you need to do [more], such as seizing equipment...
from the person(s) of interest, which would
require the due-process action of a court.
It works pretty well in terms of the
difference between secrecy and privacy.
Privacy as an individual right can be
maintained, while secrecy overall cannot.
On Bitcoin, it is much easier to achieve radical
transparency than it is to achieve anonymity.
And Bitcoin cannot be seen
on its own without the context.
The context is, there are [hundreds] of other
digital currencies created in the last two years,
based on the recipe [of Bitcoin].
[Some are] more anonymous and stealthy
than Bitcoin, and will continue to thrive regardless...
of what regulation is placed on Bitcoin.
If anything, the risk with pushing Bitcoin into a corner
[will be] like [what happened] with the music industry.
where they pushed Napster into a corner and ended
up with much more [resistant] file-sharing networks.
[MATTHEW CANAVAN] Do you think-
If we decide that this is too risky,
that it creates too great a security threat,
and we wanted to try and stamp it out...
We we can only pass laws for Australia.
How effective [could we be], even in coordination
with other countries, in stopping digital currency?
Where is it located right now? Presumably, it can
always go to a country where there aren't regulations.
Those who want to do wrong can still can still access it?
[ANDREAS] Honestly, Senator, Bitcoin and
the decentralized innovation behind Bitcoin...
have turned money and transactional
exchange into a form of information content.
You can no longer stop information
from flowing that carries bitcoin [with it]...
than you can stop information from flowing...
that carries a subversive tweet, as the
president of Turkey realized recently,
or other forms of information flow in a free society
where the internet exists and can be accessed.
[Let alone other] forms of communication.
Bitcoin will continue to exist. As long as there are
network nodes that support its block propagation,
it will continue to exist.
Regulation of the protocol itself is not possible.
[SAM DASTYARI] Edwards, would you like to jump in?
[SEAN EDWARDS] If you [don't] want to
continue with that line of questioning...
[MATTHEW CANAVAN] I am happy to ask
one more question, slightly moving along...
from the law enforcement front to tax,
not necessarily nefarious or criminal activity.
I have seen you mention it. For example, Google
could use bitcoin to do payroll all around the world,
and save a lot on transaction costs.
Of course, Google has also been subject to a fair
amount of controversy about how they pay tax,
where they pay tax, and if they pay tax. [Laughter]
We have a related inquiry into corporate tax.
I don't know if you have any information on this,
but do you think digital currencies are another
order of difficulty for taxation authorities,
in terms of tracking transfers and pricing, and
related issues about the jurisdiction of profits?
[ANDREAS] I don't think so. When products and services
can be delivered from [almost] anywhere in the world,
and [many] payments can be
transferred [in different currencies],
there is no fundamental difference in using bitcoin.
From my experience, I think it is important to realize
that most tax [report] systems are based on honesty,
and then severe punishments if you
fail to meet that standard of honesty.
When I submit a tax return, my bank account
is not audited for every transaction I have made.
That is not how it works.
However, if I lie on my tax return and am caught,
then everything I have done will be audited,
including the transactions I made in bitcoin,
which are already available on a public ledger.
Again, it doesn't really change the basic social
contract between people and their government.
Most people report their taxes honestly and try to
[access] services from their government in return.
Their use of bitcoin will only increase their
economic opportunity to [participate in]...
international trade and commerce with
people from other parts of the world.
It doesn't really change the mechanics of taxation.
It allows an individual to act more like a multi-national
company in terms of [transacting] internationally.
But certainly the unique advantage of multi-national
companies to evade, cheat, or not pay taxes anyway...
will remain as it is today.
[SAM DASTYARI] Senator Edwards?
[SEAN EDWARDS] I know we are running out of time.
Since you have just been through the Canadian inquiry,
what evidence did you hear in
that inquiry that most alarmed you?
[ANDREAS] I participated only in a short part of that.
Actually, I was very pleased with the outcome.
It seemed that the Canadian Senate was very open
to understanding the nuances of this [new] currency,
[willing] to make the type of fine distinctions necessary
between fringe use cases and the overall system.
About its behavior, as well as between the types of
activity that need to be regulated, like custodians,
versus the types of activities that put power in the hands
of individual users, such as multi-signature [schemes]...
and [non-custodial], individually controlled wallets.
I was very pleased with the outcome.
I don't think anything I heard concerned me.
[SAM DASTYARI] Just one final question, if it is okay.
I think Canavan may have a final one as well.
You said in your opening statement that it is important
to get the balance right (I am paraphrasing)...
between providing the right regulatory framework
and certainty [for] businesses, but at the same time...
not stifling the attractive qualities of innovation.
The challenge for us, and I wouldn't mind
putting this to you [as a question], is...
How do we get the balance right between what the
industry naturally wants, a regulatory framework...
to provide them certainty, so that your Visas
and Mastercards can start properly investing,
and at the same time, not creating too rigid of a
framework that effectively displaces the benefits?
I know you touched on that as being the challenge,
but [from the perspective of] regulators.
I wouldn't mind just picking your brain a
little bit on that, before before you leave.
[ANDREAS] One of the big problems in
this particular area is, we are dealing with...
very disruptive and fast-moving technology.
It has only recently emerged into the limelight.
As a result, there is a lot of uncertainty.
We don't really know where
Bitcoin will be in a couple of years,
whether it will be used primarily as a
long-term store-of-value akin to digital gold...
for [primarily] large transactions
involving [influential] parties.
As I like to say, the kind of currency
used to buy aircraft carriers with.
Or maybe it will turn into a currency used for micro,
retail transactions and consumer online commerce.
The kind of currency you [use to] buy a cup of coffee.
Or perhaps it will fill both of those
[functions] at the same time.
There are many unanswered questions at the moment.
We are seeing many perceived problems in the industry
being solved with innovation instead of regulation.
Just in the last two years, there have been tremendous
developments in security mechanisms for individuals...
to protect their bitcoin holdings against hacking
and thieves while controlling [their keys] directly,
without giving them to custodial exchanges and other
organizations, where [the bitcoin] can be easily stolen.
As I said to the Canadian Senate, a wait-and-see
approach is the most likely to be successful.
We saw with the early internet that the wait-and-see
approach allowed the network to thrive and change.
[Over time], it morphed into various different
models based on consumer adoption.
Bitcoin consumer adoption has barely started.
We don't know yet how the network will reflect the
values of a mainstream community behind it,
or what uses they will put this network to.
That is the most exciting aspect of this new technology.
I would caution one thing, however.
In the [early days] of the internet, it would have
been dangerous to allow the phone companies...
to set the rules by which the internet would operate.
They would have made sure that it wouldn't operate.
In the [early days] of the automobile, it would have been
dangerous to allow the railroads to set the rules.
Yet that is exactly what they did in
the United Kingdom with Red Flag Act,
which stalled development of the
automotive industry for decades.
It was wrong to allow the oil industry to regulate
electricity generation in the United States,
in the early years.
The incumbent industry always wants to
write the rules for their new competitors,
to make sure that they don't get a foothold.
Allowing Visa or Mastercard to define the rules
by which this new payment network will work...
will ensure they write rules that won't allow bitcoin to...
disrupt their very cozy, staid multi-billion-dollar industry.
It has been able to shield itself from
competition for more than fifty years.
It desperately needs strong competition right now,
because it has failed consumers all across the world.
[MATTHEW CANAVAN] Do we still have time, Chair?
[SAM DASTYARI] Yes, if you want to squeeze one in.
[MATTHEW CANAVAN] If that is okay,
Mr. Antonopoulos, I have two more questions.
In your view, you obviously believe that Bitcoin or digital
currency will achieve a greater penetration than today.
Do you think [more] people will use custodial accounts?
[Will they] maintain their own keys [for their
digital] cash, if you like, on their own computers?
Or you think they will use
third-parties to manage that process?
I ask that question and relate it
back to the regulatory issue.
If they do that, presumably with the transparency
and fingerprints available to authorities,
there will not be much difference
from what they currently have with banks.
[ANDREAS] I think in some environments, people will;
in other environments, they will not [or can't].
In consumer environments where banking relationships
exist and can be extended to existing populations,
custodial accounts may be the easiest way to
[become] involved in Bitcoin -- which is a shame.
I am hoping that we see enough innovation in security,
user experience and user interface design to allow...
more people to [easily] have decentralized
control over their own money, through Bitcoin.
That is the best model by which bitcoin
and other digital currencies work.
One of the interesting [developments] will be the
deployment of smartphones with digital currency...
in places of the world where banking relationships
do not exist, have never existed, and cannot exist...
simply due to lack of infrastructure and political turmoil.
There is an unwillingness [by traditional financial
services] to extend to billions and billions of people.
I am far more interested with the possibility...
of bitcoin being used on very cheap text messaging
and Android phones throughout Southeast Asia,
Indonesia, China, and many of
the places very close to Australia.
[This is] where billions of people are currently using
very primitive cash-based or barter-based systems.
Their economies are suppressed
as a result of that friction.
A very simple smartphone or feature phone could
represent not just a communication mechanism,
but a bank service window, a credit service window,
a mortgage origination or stock trading terminal,
or an [entire] import-export business.
I can imagine a kid, driving around on a scooter with
an Android phone while running a remittances business.
[With a group of such kids], they could [eventually]
deliver billions of dollars into his local economy.
In my view, that is the enduring
promise of digital currencies.
Today, banking is available to just over
three million people, on a very basic level.
Only about 1.5 billion people have...
the kind of internationally capable, currency
control-free power banking that you and I enjoy.
That leaves four to six billion people outside of the loop.
That is where I think digital currencies will be best used.
In those environments,
there is no custodial relationship.
Those people will hold the bitcoin
directly on their own devices.
[MATTHEW CANAVAN] My last question is, how long do
you think it will be before Bitcoin becomes mainstream?
[ANDREAS] The internet took fifteen years.
Cellular telephones took ten years.
The web took seven years.
Perhaps bitcoin will be even faster.
It depends on what you mean by "mainstream adoption."
I already use it, as do a couple million people already.
I think [it will take] ten or fifteen years before
it is used by people who are not technically savvy,
broadly across all of society.
But I think we will see significant
penetration in the next five years.
[MATTHEW CANAVAN] Okay, thank you.
[SAM DASTYARI] Thank you so much,
Mr. Antonopoulos, for making yourself available.
I know it was not easy with the technology
we had to use to make this work.
So, I can't thank you enough for
your participation in our inquiry.
[ANDREAS] Fortunately, the phone companies
didn't write the regulations for the internet,
and that is why I was able to do this today.
[Laughter] Thank you!
[VARIOUS MEMBERS] Good luck,
good on you. Thank you, Andreas!